<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A conciliatory discourse upon Dr. Crisp's sermons on the observation of Mr. William's dissatisfactions in them : in which the unsearchable riches of Christ ... / by T. Beverley.</title>
            <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 111 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27592</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2134</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34407</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14398025</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14398025</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102302</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27592)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102302)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1056:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A conciliatory discourse upon Dr. Crisp's sermons on the observation of Mr. William's dissatisfactions in them : in which the unsearchable riches of Christ ... / by T. Beverley.</title>
                  <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 88 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Marshall ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages cropped with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Crisp, Tobias, 1600-1643. --  Christ alone exalted.</term>
               <term>Williams, Daniel, 1643?-1716. --  Gospel-truth stated and vindicated.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102302:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102302:1"/>
            <p> A Conciliatory DISCOURSE UPON Dr. Criſp's Sermons, ON THE <hi>Obſervation of Mr.</hi> Williams<hi>'s Diſſatisfactions in Them:</hi> In which the Unſearcheable Riches of Chriſt IN THE Covenant of Grace, paſſing Knowledge, is yet Aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to, to be made Known.</p>
            <p>Humbly Preſented To the Preachers of the Merchants Lecture at <hi>Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners-Hall;</hi> To the Suſtainers of it, And the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation uſually Aſſembled there.</p>
            <p>By <hi>T. BEVERLEY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>William Marſhall,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Newgate-ſtreet,</hi> 1692. Where you may be furniſhed with Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi>'s Works: And likewiſe his Son's Book, <hi>Samuel Criſp,</hi> Eſq; Entitul'd, <hi>Chriſt made Sin.</hi> You may alſo be ſupplied <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:102302:2"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:102302:2"/>
            <p> I Have (not long ago) endeavour'd to Write as a Reconciler, between Two Perſons of Eſtimable Memory; Dr. <hi>Criſp,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baxter;</hi> Now Both in their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits with Christ; where They have Fully Concerted their ſeeming various Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions, or Repreſentations in ſo Great Points; not only by Receiving thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, thoſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n-utterable Explanations of them; but in their Highest En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments, and Mutual Congratulations, in thoſe Fundamental Truths, and Graces; wherein they were, even here, notwithſtanding a ſeeeming Diſcord, (and much more there) One in Christ.</p>
            <p>But we, that are on this ſide their Line, ſtill <hi>See through a Glaſs Darkly,</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, Know and Speak as <hi>Children;</hi> and ſo Expreſs our ſelves Diverſly, one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as we look to this, or that ſide of Truth: Not being able to Comprehend the perfect Phyſiognomy, or Repreſentation of it at once.</p>
            <p>And indeed in the Great Points, that are nearest allied to the Coveant of Grace, we are most unable to pronounce clearly; That first Engraving upon our Hearts, and the Divine Revelation of Christ, <hi>(From Faith,</hi> Rom. 1. 17. having not yet Attain'd <hi>To Faith,</hi> in Perfection) are ready in this our Imperfect State, to enter a Centest in our Minds; and we cannot decide, as we ought, between the <hi>Eternal Law</hi> of <hi>Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and the <hi>Everlaſting Goſpel</hi> of <hi>Righteouſneſs:</hi> and while we have Great Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſes in Scripture upon Both, we very hardly keep the <hi>Ballance of the Sanctuary even</hi> in our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings, as it is in it ſelf: While therefore the Servants of Christ are, ſome in their Miniſtry, inclining the Beam one way, and ſome another; though accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the manifold Diſtributions of one and the ſame Spirit to both in the main; yet they are ready to find fault mutually at their ſo doing: It may be no Injury then for a Third, to endeavour to ſet Both even, though great Infirmity may appear in that alſo: For <hi>who is ſufficient for theſe Things?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eſpecially it is to be conſider'd, The Goſpel-Righteouſneſs, or of <hi>Faith,</hi> hath ever ſince the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Preaching and Writing, ſuffer'd an Eclipſe by the <hi>Myſtery of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity</hi> early working; and by degrees, from that very time, the Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtle dates, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. it was cover'd more and more. Till the very State of the Chriſtian Church fell into the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Dark</hi> and <hi>Foul Place</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> 2 Pet. 1. 19. And though the Eclipſe be much leſs than it was, by the Light returning in the <hi>Reformation;</hi> yet it remains in part; and oh that it were not in Great part! Now it is very obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, That grand <hi>Prophecy</hi> of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> knowing upon what ſide of Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Truth that Black Shade would most dreadfully fall, gives its Divine <hi>Symbols</hi> or moſt Exquiſite Figures for prevention; for preſervation of the Witneſſes of Chriſt; for Condemnation of the Apoſtacy; for Recovery out of it; in this Supreme Article of Goſpel-Truth; <hi>the Blood of Chriſt.</hi> Hence there are ſo often mentions of the <hi>Lamb;</hi> of his <hi>Blood;</hi> of <hi>Robes waſh'd white in his Blood.</hi> The pure and perfect <hi>Song of the Lamb,</hi> as it was ſung in the Apoſtles Days, is given, <hi>chap.</hi> 5. as the Great Standard. The <hi>Witneſſes</hi> are within the <hi>meaſur'd Temple,</hi> during the whole <hi>Apoſtacy.</hi> Which <hi>Temple</hi> is the known Type of Christ in his Redemption; They are at the <hi>Golden Altar of Incenſe,</hi> the pure Interceſſion of Chriſt in the deep of the <hi>Apoſtacy.</hi> Along the entire ſpace of which, that <hi>New Song of the Lamb,</hi> chap. 5. is almost wholly lost. The
<pb facs="tcp:102302:3"/> Apoſtacy is thus condemn'd, <hi>ch.</hi> 13. 8. All the Earth <hi>Worſhipp'd</hi> the <hi>Antichriſtian Beaſt;</hi> whoſe <hi>Names were not written</hi> in the <hi>Lamb's Book of Life, ſlain from the Foundation of the World.</hi> The difference is not very great, whether we apply the last words to the <hi>Lamb ſlain,</hi> or <hi>Names written.</hi> I prefer the first, ſhewing the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity of the Sacrifice of Chriſt, above the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pſtarts of <hi>Antichriſtianiſm.</hi> At the end of the <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> when the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> Seal'd on their <hi>Foreheads</hi> appear'd with the <hi>Name written</hi> there (as I have further intimated in the following Diſcourſe) The <hi>Song</hi> as it were <hi>new,</hi> becauſe ſo much Lost, is <hi>Sung</hi> again with the <hi>Voice of Thunder,</hi> and to be <hi>Learnt, chap.</hi> 14. and is perfectly Learnt, <hi>chap.</hi> 15. after the <hi>Preaching of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Goſpel.</hi> There the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Redemption,</hi> in its fully Glory, follows, wherein the Saints are <hi>Prieſts,</hi> not <hi>only of God,</hi> but <hi>of Chriſt,</hi> a 1000 Years, <hi>chap.</hi> 20. 6. Have the <hi>Name</hi> not only of <hi>God,</hi> but of the <hi>Lamb,</hi> written on their Foreheads. And the <hi>Throne of God,</hi> and <hi>the Lamb</hi> is in that <hi>City of Redemption,</hi> c. 22. 3, 4.</p>
            <p>And it is most notorious Matter of Fact, that the moſt Glorious Ray of the <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> was the Reſtoration of the Doctrine of <hi>Juſtification</hi> by Free Grace, and Faith in Jeſus; wherein <hi>Luther,</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> with other <hi>Reformers,</hi> however in other things they differ'd, yet concurr'd herein, as under the <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Zeal</hi> of <hi>Elijah,</hi> All in it. How much any under the Profeſſion of the <hi>Reformation</hi> have declin'd from this; <hi>Ipſi Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derint,</hi> Let them well look to it. I am far from eſteeming the Reverend Perſons I have to do with, Dead, or Living, among that ſort.</p>
            <p>But this Great Fall of the <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> as from Heaven, in this Point, would tempt any conſidering Perſon to be moſt on the ſide of thoſe, who aſcribe moſt to Free Grace, and the Righteouſneſs of God in Chriſt; Except they hold the <hi>Doctrine</hi> or <hi>Deeds of the Nicolaitans,</hi> the <hi>Turning the Grace of God into Laſciviouſneſs, which Thing Chriſt hates,</hi> ch. 2. 6, 15. being the other part of <hi>Antichriſtianiſm; Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences to Sin:</hi> And this I never heard Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi> charg'd with; and he is particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acquitted by his Reverend Oppoſite.</p>
            <p>I dare not pretend to juſtifie all my own, much leſs anothers Expreſſions, who knew his own Grounds and Reaſons of ſo expreſſing; and, it is most probable, thought ſome unu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual ones neceſſary to alarm the Thoughts and Minds of Men into the Obſervation of the Truths he deſign'd to exalt, as not enough exalted.</p>
            <p>I do not pretend to enter, as they ſay, the Liſts with ſo Judicious and Worthy a Perſon, as Mr. <hi>Williams;</hi> nor with the Things he hath ſpoken, giving a Cordial Aſſent to much the moſt; nor ſhall I, I hope, appear <hi>Contentious,</hi> wherein I diſſent; but have only conſider'd, what Truth lies on each hand, more than what he himſelf hath ſo excellently obſerv'd; and have therefore made his Heads at the end of his Book the Line of my Procedure, and ſo have ſet them at the end of this.</p>
            <p>I commit all to Divine Bleſſing, and Chriſtian Acceptation, with this gladſom Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; that if we can but for a little, a very little time, <hi>love the Truth,</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> Zech. 8. 19. The Light concerning theſe Points, that hath been but as the <hi>Light of the Moon</hi> in the time of the 42 <hi>Moons</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> not yet expir'd, and ſo ſtill darkning the Sun's Light; ſhall be not only as the <hi>Light of the Sun</hi> of Chriſt's Face; <hi>ch.</hi> 10. 1. in the <hi>Reformation;</hi> But the <hi>Light of the Sun,</hi> even ſince the <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> ſhall be <hi>Seven-fold;</hi> the <hi>Light of One Day,</hi> as the <hi>Light of Seven,</hi> All in One. Then we ſhall Rejoyce, and no longer Diſſent. Let us Earneſtly Pray: Lord, Let (as it ſhall ſhortly do) <hi>Thy Kingdom</hi> thus <hi>Come.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:102302:3"/>
            <head>A SECOND Conciliatory Diſcourſe CONCERNING Dr. Criſp's Sermons, AND Mr. <hi>Williams</hi>'s Diſſatisfactions concerning them.</head>
            <p>THat which I would lay in the Foundation and as the Center of this Diſcourſe, ſhall be a Scheme of the Doctrine of the Goſpel in theſe Points.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Covenant of Grace in all the Graces and Duties of the Convenantees of it, God in infinite Wiſdom, Holineſs and Purity hath ſo ſetled, that it is an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Covenant, in which Chriſt is not only the Great Sacrifice, and his Blood the Price, Ranſom, and Purchaſe; But He Himſelf is the <hi>Surety,</hi> the <hi>Mediator,</hi> the <hi>Teſtator</hi> of it: So that This Covenant ſhall never be <hi>Found Fault</hi> with. Not only on the Account of its own Goodneſs; but not on this Account, that the Covenantees, or thoſe who are indeed intended by Chriſt to be the Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees, have <hi>broken</hi> it, and ſo it hath become ineffectual to them. This is moſt evident from the Apoſtle's Argumentation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8, 7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For if the <hi>First Covenant</hi> had been <hi>faultleſs,</hi> there ſhould have been no <hi>place ſought for a ſecond:</hi> The firſt Covenant, that God made, was in it ſelf good, had they to whom it was given, been ſuitable and agreeable to it; The Apoſtle therefore changes that his word, if the <hi>Covenant</hi> had be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>faultleſs,</hi> into thoſe words. For <hi>finding fault with them,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Behold the Days come, ſaith the Lord, I will make a new Covenant, not according to the Covenant I made with their Fathers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>which my Covenant they brake, or continued not in, and I regarded them not. But this is the Covenant I will make with them, I will write my Laws in their Hearts,</hi> &amp;c. Hence it follows, The Covenantees according to the <hi>faultleſs Covenant</hi> muſt ſo <hi>continue</hi> in it, that God may be for <hi>ever their God,</hi> and <hi>they his People;</hi> there need be no diſpute, what Covenant this was, or in what regard it is here ſpoken of; whether only as a Covenant of Moral Obedience, or as a Ritual Ceremonial Covenant; for it is
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:102302:4"/> undeniable, the Apoſtle repreſents it herein as a <hi>Covenant found fault with,</hi> that <hi>they who were under it continued not in it;</hi> and therefore whatever Covenant, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Moral or Ceremonial, had that <hi>Fault</hi> to be <hi>found</hi> with it, God would change, and bring in a Covenant, that ſhould not have that <hi>Fault</hi> to be <hi>found</hi> with it: It muſt and ſhall be effectual to the grand purpoſe of keeping in the People of it ſo within it ſelf, as to be <hi>God's People,</hi> and that he will be <hi>their God;</hi> ſuch ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacies of Grace ſhall all go along with it: This is not to be eluded by any Art or Wit of Man.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From hence it muſt neceſſarily follow, There is a certain number <hi>choſen</hi> and <hi>elected</hi> according to the Grace of this Covenant, and for them this <hi>Covenant is made.</hi> For it is too evident in plain view, and as matter of fact, that the moſt Gracious and Spiritual Covenant of the Goſpel does not thus embrace all that are under it in profeſſion, as that <hi>God ſhould be for ever their God,</hi> and <hi>they his People,</hi> and that they ſhould be for ever pardon'd. Seeing yet, <hi>2dly,</hi> it is God, and Chriſt, that look to it, that this Covenant ſhould be thus continued in; And, <hi>3dly,</hi> that Scripture, ſpeaking of thoſe thus ſecur'd according to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, ſtiles them, <hi>The Election,</hi> and continually ſpeaks of the <hi>Election of Grace,</hi> the <hi>Riches of Grace,</hi> and the <hi>Glory and Praiſe of Grace,</hi> not of <hi>Works,</hi> but <hi>of Him that calleth.</hi> All this put together, ſhews a certain Number <hi>elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> In reſpect to whom this <hi>Covenant</hi> ſhall not be <hi>faulted</hi> for their <hi>breaking</hi> it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Election</hi> is in Jeſus Chriſt the <hi>Head,</hi> of the <hi>Adoption,</hi> the <hi>First born a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong many Brethren,</hi> even all the <hi>Sons God will bring Glory through Him:</hi> So Jeſus Chriſt muſt be the Supreme and Chief in the whole Doctrine of Salvation; His Blood, and Death, his Righteouſneſs, and Obedience, His Appearance with that Blood in Heaven, in his <hi>Melchiſedecian</hi> Prieſthood; and there by the <hi>Power of an Endleſs Life,</hi> Negotiating, and Tranſacting all for, and in his Servants, as by a perpetual Rotation of that Power, as in a Sphere of higheſt Activity, by his Spirit. Theſe are the very Powers of Salvation.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This the Scripture repreſents to be Eternal, or from before the <hi>Foundation of the World:</hi> which is the conſtant Expreſſion it uſes to convey to us the Notion of Eternity by; now Eternal ſurrounds and encompaſſes Time, and gives all the efficacy to the Motions in and upon it; for as it encircles it, ſo it penetrates it every where, with infinity of Lines cutting it every way: ſo that though to us, as Creatures of Times, theſe two, Time and Eternity, ſeem moſt diſtinct, and are ſo ſpoken of; yet indeed Time is ſupported, and in all Parts and Lines of it interwoven by Eternity.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Supreme Repreſentation of God in the whole State of our Salvation, is as of a Father in Chriſt; this is moſt demonſtrative, ſeeing it is to the <hi>Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Children,</hi> we are <hi>choſen,</hi> which neceſſarily carries the notion of a Father; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo it is the <hi>making conformable to the Image of his Son;</hi> and ſeeing it is for the <hi>bringing many Sons to glory.</hi> And ſo Jeſus Chriſt is repreſented in the neareſt and moſt intimate Relations, as the <hi>First-born among many Brethren,</hi> yea, ſometimes as a <hi>Father,</hi> as a <hi>Husband,</hi> as a <hi>Root to the Branches,</hi> as a <hi>Head to the Members.</hi> This is the moſt inward and intimate Repreſentation of Scripture concerning our Salvation.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb facs="tcp:102302:4"/> 6. But the Outward, and more extern Adminiſtration is by God, <hi>the Judge of all,</hi> or the Rector and Governor of all; and by Jeſus Chriſt, as <hi>Lord of all,</hi> and he, as <hi>having all Judgment committed to him,</hi> is made known to us. But though the Elect Children of God and Members of Chriſt, are comprehended in ſeveral ways of Scripture-ſpeaking under this Outward Adminiſtration; yet This Outward Adminiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation is chiefly with regard to the Non-Elect, to clear and juſtify God in all his Dealings with them; and therefore as to the exterior part of his Adminiſtration, there are the ſame Overtures made to the one, that there are to the other; and the one are ſav'd, and brought home to God, under the ſame means, the other are loſt.</p>
            <p n="7">7. This Inward Grace, and the Outward Adminiſtration exceedingly differ; For the Inward Grace, is Love, Spirit, Life; the Outward Adminiſtration, is (to ſpeak nothing now of the Government of Chriſt, by the Laws and Light of Nature, where his Word is not in Outward Adminiſtration) where it is, by the Overtures of his Word upon the Underſtanding, Wills, Affections and Conſciences, of his Subjects one with another; By that Miniſtry of his Word, he preſſes upon all, the <hi>Obedience</hi> of Faith, Repentance and Holyneſs, the Duties, required of us; which, according to the Inward Grace and Love to his own, he gives the Inward Efficacy and Almighty Operation of:</p>
            <p n="8">8. In the Inward Grace, and the Operations of it, there is a veſting them in the Faculties of his <hi>Election,</hi> and a Conduct of their Internal Action upon their own Minds and Hearts; and of the Principles of Outward Action, which flow in all Conformity and Agreeableneſs thereunto; ſo that the Vehicle is our ſelves, but the Inſpiration is God's and Chriſt's.</p>
            <p n="9">9. From all this it is evident, That although there is on many Accounts, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be given, a large Field and Scope of Preaching and Diſcourſing upon, and according to the outward Adminiſtration; yet it is of Superior Neceſſity, to preſerve the Fountains of Grace and Love, of Power and Spirit clear, the Foundations ſure and firm; and though there may be Fault in not being large enough upon, and according to the outward Adminiſtration; becauſe it ſhews the neceſſity of, and, as a School-maſter, brings to the Inward, and manifeſts how it diffuſes it ſelf; yet the Error and Danger is greater, in not ſufficiently both ſecuring and illuſtrating the Doctrin of the Inward Grace. For many more have periſh'd in ſticking upon the Outward, without being led in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, than by applying moſt to the Inward. For that always, when it is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd ador'd and receiv'd, diffuſes it ſelf into the Outward. So that if Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Love and Grace is Chriſt, be ſo taught, as that its Efficacyes are always ſhewn to be in all Holyneſs and Purity; If it pleaſes the All-wiſe Spirit to carry any of the Spirits of his Servants, wholly upon the Inward Grace; ſeeing he ballances them by many Men of his Servants, largely inſiſting upon the Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Adminiſtration, therefore ſuch his Servants are not to be blam'd; but God is to be acknowledg'd in his manifold Graces and unſpeakable Gifts, by the one, and by the other.</p>
            <p n="10">10. The Glorious Appearance of all theſe, is not, till in the <hi>Fulneſs,</hi> not only of <hi>Time,</hi> as in our Lord's Coming, but in the <hi>Fulneſs of Times</hi> viz. of all <hi>Time</hi> in the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> Then ſhall be a Recollection, a Recapitulation, a Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering,
<pb facs="tcp:102302:5"/> and a <hi>Gathering together of all in Chriſt;</hi> Then ſhall the Riches of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Grace be <hi>found</hi> to <hi>Praiſe</hi> and <hi>Glory;</hi> And the Wiſdom, Righteouſneſs, and admirable <hi>Long-Suffering</hi> and Patience of the External Adminiſtration and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of God and Chriſt, as Rector and Judge of the Univerſe, be admir'd and ador'd alſo towards, even the Loſt.</p>
            <p>Having thus laid a general Scheme, I come now particularly to make brief Conciliations of the true and moſt enlarg'd Apprehenſions, and Diſcourſes, upon even Eternal free Grace in Chriſt towards all the Elect of God, according to Dr. <hi>Criſp,</hi> with Mr. <hi>Williams</hi>'s weighty, and moſt valuable Conſiderations up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Outward Adminiſtration of the Goſpel Covenant, according to his Heads of Diſcourſe at the end of his Book.</p>
            <div n="1" type="head">
               <head>Head 1.</head>
               <p>To the firſt Head: <q rend="margQuotes">The <hi>Elect are Children of Wrath,</hi> till <hi>effectually call'd;</hi> As it may be oppos'd to all Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi> hath ſaid concerning the <hi>Elect,</hi> being before Faith and Repentance, as much deliver'd from Wrath, even as the Believer is, or as a Saint Triumphant in Heaven is.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Reconciliation.</label> If we ſpeak, as Creatures of Time, the <hi>Elect</hi> are <hi>Children of Wrath;</hi> but why may there not be a Declaration of that great and ſupreme Truth, ſetting out the Eternal Love of God in Chriſt to all his <hi>Elect,</hi> even while they are of, and in themſelves in the <hi>Gall of Bitterneſs,</hi> and under <hi>the Bond of Iniquity?</hi> For without Relation to the <hi>having done Good</hi> or <hi>Evil,</hi> in the mere Eſtate of Nature, which is in fallen Men a State of <hi>Wrath.</hi> It is ſaid, <hi>Jacob have I loved:</hi> Now what more contrary to the State of a <hi>Child of Wrath,</hi> than to be <hi>Loved</hi> of God? So concerning Reconciliation as by the <hi>Death</hi> of Chriſt, the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>God commendeth his Love to us,</hi> in that while we were yet <hi>Sinners, Chriſt dyed for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly: When we were Enemies, we were reconciled to God by the Death of his Son.</hi> Rom. 5, 8, 10.</p>
               <p>Here then is the Caſe, God the Supreme and Eternal Being beholds all things, in, as they ſpeak, a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a juſt now; even Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> however ſo great an Enemy to a particular <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> acknowledges this view of all things by the Eternal Being: The Queſtion then is, Whether an Eternity of Love and Grace, an Eternal Duration in Happineſs, after the ſhort time of Life, and ſome parts of that ſhort time of Life reſcu'd from Wrath alſo, may not preponderate in giving the Denomination to the <hi>Elect?</hi> Or why may not the Preaching of Gods Infinite and Eternal Love and Grace, be made an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Divine Spirit for the winning in the Souls of his Elect to himſelf? When God ſays, I have <hi>Loved thee with an everlaſting Love, therefore with loving Kindneſs have I drawn thee,</hi> Jer. 31 3. Or why ſhould an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Man hereupon preſume to <hi>continue in Sin?</hi> When it is agreed on both Parts; Electing Love and Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation by the Death of Chriſt have moſt indiſpenſable efficacious Emanations into Holyneſs; while therefore there is a black and dark ſide of being paſs'd over by God, hanging over all, continuing in Impurity, to work upon Men by Terror and Affrightment out of Sin; why may not the ſetting out that Grace Work every way effectually, both by the <hi>Bands of Love,</hi> and the <hi>Goads</hi> of Fear, to move Perſons home to Chriſt? and we know Men are naturally deſirous of, and ever Induſtrious after, whatever they account Tokens, of what they call being Born to good Fortune; and as naturally fly from all the Marks, of what is
<pb facs="tcp:102302:5"/> call'd ill Fortune; I ſee therefore no Reaſon, but it ſhould ſtrongly affect Men, among whom Scripture is ſetledly receiv'd, and ſo ought to be univerſally Preached; when they hear of ſo Gracious a Choice of God, to deſire with great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Vehemency, to find in themſelves, any Manifeſtations of it, (it being the ſureſt Ground of Hope) and to be under the Dread of any of the black Marks of Rejection, as being paſs'd by of God; Of which Efficacious Holyneſs, or Unholineſs are reſpectively the Tokens and Indications.</p>
               <p>And though it muſt be acknowledg'd, There is a Point of Time, in which God ſpeaking, as in the Language of Time, does ſtyle his <hi>Elect, Children of Wrath,</hi> even <hi>as others;</hi> Yet ſpeaking in the Language of Eternity, he calls them, <hi>Veſſels of Mercy, Veſſels unto Honour;</hi> And indeed whatever is looked upon as only a Motion or Ordination of Time, muſt needs ariſe from our ſelves; For all Acts of Grace are Eternal in their Spring and Fountain; Time therefore genders only to a Covenant of Works. I know not therefore, but why, as the generality of Preachers enlarge moſt upon the one, as to unconverted <hi>Elect,</hi> There may not be ſome ſtirr'd up and enabled of God, to triumph in the <hi>Savour</hi> of the <hi>Knowledg of Chriſt,</hi> made known by them in the other; while they Center upon the <hi>Eteral Election,</hi> of God demonſtrating it ſelf, in Calling, Converſion, Sanctification: But they only can do this, who have receiv'd it, as a peculiar Talent. But I doubt not, the Spirit of it will within ſhort time be pour'd out more abundantly, and that it ſhall not turn to Licentiouſneſs, but overflow with Holyneſs and Purity, as alſo Efficacy of Converſion.</p>
               <p>The third Head I Tranſpoſe into the ſecond Place, as being more Congenial, or of a kind with the firſt; and will joyn the ſecond with the fourth and thoſe following, to Head 8th.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="head">
               <head>Head 2.</head>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">The laying the Sins of the Elect upon Chriſt is not their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge from their Sins; This is oppos'd to what Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi> hath ſaid; All the Weight, and all the Burden of Sin, the very Sin it ſelf is long ago laid upon Chriſt; and that laying it on him, is a full Diſcharge and Releaſe to that, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>The Conciliation.</label> To an Eternal Being, there muſt needs be an Eternal Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, becauſe there is no new thing to him; The Apoſtle therefore makes the whole Chain of Salvation of an Eternal <hi>old Style; whom he Foreknew, he Called, he Juſtified, he Glorified;</hi> Rom. 8. 30. All in the Time paſs'd, not in the Style of Time, but of Eternity: But when we ſpeak in <hi>new Style,</hi> Style of Time; there is not an actual Diſcharge of Sin, or a Juſtification of a Sinner by Election; but according to the order of things fix'd by God in Time; Even ſo if we conſider Sins lay'd upon Chriſt, even the Sins of all the Elect in the <hi>Fulneſs of Time,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſtyles it, That Fulneſs of Time may be very well ſuppoſed to col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect into it ſelf all Time; And as the Sins that were paſt were Recollected, ſo the Sins to come were Forepriz'd into it: And all this iſſues into the <hi>Fulneſs</hi> of <hi>Times,</hi> that is, of all Time in the Kingdom of Chriſt; For as Chriſt dyed in the <hi>Fullneſs of Time,</hi> ſo the Glory of his Redemption appears in the <hi>Fulneſs of Times,</hi> Eph. 1. 10. of All <hi>Time,</hi> when <hi>all Things,</hi> in <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> ſhall be <hi>Recapitulated</hi> in him, which yet, we know, they are not. The Offering of Chriſt therefore
<pb facs="tcp:102302:6"/> is an <hi>Offering once for all;</hi> and it is <hi>one Offering,</hi> that <hi>forever Perfects;</hi> and <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt is Yeſterday and to Day the ſame forever;</hi> As then all Time is gather'd into that <hi>Fulneſs of Time,</hi> So that <hi>Fulneſs of Time</hi> redounds upon all Time, and Flows out upon it, till it Flows into that <hi>Fulneſs of Times.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, as the Lord of Time, <hi>offered Himſelf</hi> in the <hi>Fulneſs of Time;</hi> he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piated all Sins in that <hi>Fulneſs,</hi> and what was expiated in the <hi>Fulneſs,</hi> can never be charged in the Retail of Time, for then it was not expiated.</p>
               <p>Although therefore, when we are ſpoken of, and unto, as not the Lords of Time, but the Subjects of Time, we are oblig'd to meaſure it out by Parts, as being Inferiors to it; and below the Hill to it, we ſee the Approaches of its Events, one after another only; but the Lord Paramount of it, being ſo high above it, ſees all at once; we are Creatures but of the Parts of it; ſo indeed we are not Diſcharged from Sin in the Diſcharge of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>But from hence to conclude, we are not in higheſt Senſe Diſcharg'd, but that, if the <hi>Elect</hi> dye before Faith and Repentance, they are loſt for ever, is to make ſuppoſition of Impoſſibilities; it is to ſet Time, the ſmall outlet of Eternity, to riſe up and Encounter, and lead Captive Eternity; even the Eternity of <hi>Election;</hi> and that the parts of Time may be ſet in Battel Array, and ſubdue the <hi>Fulneſs of Time.</hi> But this can by no ſerious Conſiderer be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd; I find not then, but as there is juſt Reaſon to repreſent to Men, that till they find within themſelves the Efficacies of the Death and Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of Chriſt by Faith and Repentance, they ſtand in the ſight of their own Conſciences, as Perſons, who have no Intereſt in that Death, in that Redemption; And that this is proper on one ſide, repreſenting God and Chriſt, therein as the Rector and Governor of the World, to move them to Repentance; and it is that which Scripture does very largely and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently inſiſt upon; So on the other ſide, it is moſt true, That the <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of God ſtands ſure</hi> and cannot ſhake, nor totter even under this very Seal ſingle and alone; <hi>That the Lord knows who are his,</hi> and that his <hi>Election</hi> ſhall break out with all the mighty Effects he hath pitch'd upon, as moſt ſuitable and Connatural to it; So that it ſhall produce in all its own the Derivative Stamp; <hi>Let him, that nameth the Name of Chriſt, depart from all Iniquity:</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 19. And that Chriſt is, in all Senſes, the Certain and Infallible <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifier of his People by his Blood;</hi> That he not only as a Judge, and a Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver, but as a <hi>Prince, gives Repentance</hi> and <hi>Remiſſion of Sins;</hi> This may be as hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to move the Spirits of Men, and be as gracious a Conveyance of the mighty Efficacy of the Divine Grace and Spirit; For as theſe are rich Truths of Scripture, ſo they have an admirable mooving Stroke upon the Hearts and Minds of Men; And he that Miniſters them, is a Miniſter far more immediately <hi>of the Spirit,</hi> that <hi>giveth Life;</hi> of that without which the Evangelick Law is <hi>a Letter that kills.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3-8" type="heads">
               <head>Head 3, <hi>to</hi> Head 8.</head>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">I put theſe Heads together, becauſe there cannot be any difference in the main Notions, but only in the different ways of Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and what each part may think, will moſt lively illuſtrate and make the deepeſt imprint of the great Scripture-truths upon the Heart; I ſay, there
<pb facs="tcp:102302:6"/> can be no difference in the main Truths between Perſons ſober, and Reverent of God, and of Chriſt; for who can think the filth of Sin tranſacted on Chriſt in ſuch a ſenſe, as that Chriſt ſhould be defiled by it?</q>
               </p>
               <p>But now there muſt needs be a Moral Impurity in every Sin, as it is a Receſs from the Holineſs of God, from the Righteouſneſs of the Divine Law; there is a Diſhonour, a Blot, a Stain and Blemiſh, a Deformity, a loſs of Beauty and Honour, and Happy Conformity to Goodneſs and Righteouſneſs. This is intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Reatus Culpae,</hi> another thing from the <hi>Reatus Poenae,</hi> or a meer Obligation to Puniſhment. I demand then, What becomes of this Obliquity, the Guilt of the very Fault of Sin reſting upon the Sinner? Sure thoſe Acts of Diſhonour do not remain upon the beautified Believer in Chriſt; How then can it be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? The Acts of Holineſs a Believer does, cannot purge it; for there is Impuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in them; nor are they able to raſe the Records: If then they be taken off, ſurely it muſt be by the Supreme Obedience, Righteouſneſs, Sanctification of Jeſus Chriſt, by the tranſcendent Act of Holineſs, and Reſignation to the Divine Will; the Glory, and Honour and Perfection of which imputed to the Believer, is able to <hi>ſanctifie</hi> him; as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>John</hi> 17. <hi>I ſanctifie my ſelf,</hi> I draw up my Obedience to the higheſt point of Holineſs, by that abſolute, perfect Reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to the Will of my Father, <hi>for their ſakes,</hi> that they by the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of that very Holineſs <hi>might be ſanctified in Truth;</hi> that is the Moral Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purity, and Obliquity and Diſhonour of the Sins they have committed may be removed. So <hi>Sanctification,</hi> thus ſpoken of may be ſomething higher than a Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication only in <hi>Foro Poenae,</hi> if I may ſo ſpeak, in the Court, where puniſhment is conſider'd, but in <hi>Foro Honoris,</hi> in the Court of Honour, where Attaints are purg'd off, and Blood, as they ſpeak, reſtor'd. If there be only acquittal from Guilt, binding over to Puniſhment; even the Blemiſh, the Stain, Taint, and Diſhonour Sin brings and leaves, is not effaced. This the high Honour of the Holineſs and perfect Purity of Chriſt, eſpecially in obedience to Death, even the Death of the Croſs, fully purges off, as imputed to all his; by which they are not only delivered from Puniſhment, but <hi>conſtituted Righteous,</hi> Rom. 5. By the <hi>Will of God ſo fulfill'd, they are ſanctified,</hi> in the ſenſe given; and he hath by <hi>one Offering, perfected</hi> or <hi>conſecrated,</hi> ennobled them in Blood to be <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Prieſts,</hi> by the Imputation of the Honour of Holineſs to <hi>Them that are ſanctified;</hi> and that <hi>he might ſanctifie his People by his own Blood, he ſuffered without the Gate;</hi> He hath <hi>loved,</hi> and <hi>waſhed us from our Sins in his own Blood,</hi> to <hi>make us Kings and Prieſts, (Heb.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 13.) From them all the <hi>Labes,</hi> the <hi>Macula,</hi> the Spot of Sin is taken off, and he <hi>preſents his Church without Spot, Wrinkle,</hi> or any <hi>ſuch Thing,</hi> and without Blame, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1. This is the Higheſt and moſt Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Notion of the Redemption of Chriſt, and may deſerve a Rhetorick, that may ſeem extravagant, like <hi>David</hi>'s <hi>dancing</hi> before the <hi>Ark,</hi> not ſo grave and ſo ſolemn; that may <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> conſtrain, or tranſport rather, it being before ſo gracious a Redeemer.</p>
               <p>Now if Chriſt takes off the Stain and Diſhonour of Sin, it muſt be laid upon Him; on which account it is ſaid, <hi>Eſay</hi> 53. <hi>He was Number'd among Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors,</hi> as a ſhade of this Truth; and it is ſpoken of Chriſt, though he was <hi>ſeparate</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:102302:7"/> 
                  <hi>from ſinners,</hi> yet as if he offered for his <hi>own ſins,</hi> he needed not daily, as <hi>thoſe Prieſts,</hi> Heb. 7. 27. <hi>offer for his own ſins;</hi> and <hi>God laid upon him the Iniquities of us All;</hi> and <hi>he was made ſin for us, who knew no ſin.</hi> And he was in the <hi>likeneſs of ſinful fleſh.</hi> And it is made the Diſtinction of his <hi>Second Appearance,</hi> that he <hi>appears the ſecond time without ſin to ſalvation,</hi> Heb. 9. 28. thereby ſignifying his <hi>First Appearance</hi> was as much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſin, as it could be without inherent ſin; He went as a <hi>leprous,</hi> a <hi>defiled,</hi> an <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed Perſon,</hi> a Criminal of Diſhonour <hi>without the Camp,</hi> and <hi>without the Gate;</hi> all under a Divine Ordination, to <hi>put him</hi> to <hi>open ſhame,</hi> as under the diſhonour of ſin. By all which it appears, Chriſt as our <hi>Surety</hi> and <hi>Mediator,</hi> as our <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, every way bare as deep a ſhare of adherency in our ſin, as could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt with an unſpotted Purity from any inherency of ſin in himſelf, and hereunto all Scripture expreſſion even labours. And if Humane Speaking, endeavouring to fathom and expound ſuch Expreſſions, as may moſt be to the Capacity, and to make impreſſion upon Hearers, (For is there not a cauſe?) If there be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing Humane found, and not with the admirable exactneſs of Scripture, it ought not to be ſo much expos'd; for, I doubt not, our Expreſſions fall gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally more too ſhort of the Divine Senſe of Scripture in theſe things, than other good Mens exceed; it being always to be firmly believ'd, no good Man, while he ſo ſpoke, could have it once enter into his thoughts; That there could the leaſt ſhade of proper Inherent Filth fall, or enter into the Humanity of the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator,</hi> united to the <hi>Eternal Word;</hi> However Scripture, however he might <hi>thus ſpeak,</hi> as hath been declar'd. But theſe things cannot, ſince the ſpeaking of Scripture it ſelf, if we go about by Preaching to enlarge upon them, be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of ſo accurately, but we either add or diminiſh from ſpeaking this thing as it is; nor ſhall we be able; till within a ſhort time, That, <hi>as it were, new Song be ſung on Mount Zion,</hi> Rev. 14. Then I truſt we ſhall learn it.</p>
               <p>Even ſo, That our Sins are our own, and not Chriſts, is moſt true in the ſenſe intended; yet that they became Chriſts in his great <hi>Offering for Sin,</hi> and that they are neither Believers, nor Chriſts when he had <hi>born them off</hi> in a ſenſe worthy of and agreeable to the Goſpel; The ſetting out Sin then as our own, for Humiliation, Faith, and Repentance, is moſt Evangelical; So to ſet them out, ſo Chriſt's, in his act of ſuffering, as to repreſent him a <hi>perfect Offering</hi> for them, and neither ours, nor Chriſt's, when he had born them away; and God upon it ſo acquitted Chriſt, as to caſt them into <hi>the depths of Sea,</hi> ſo that when <hi>they are ſought for, there ſhall be none to be found,</hi> and plainly <hi>none, Jer.</hi> 50. 20. This is moſt Evangelical alſo, and muſt be the ſublimeſt Evangelical; becauſe, abating the ſhort moments of time, in which it may be otherwiſe repreſented, it is eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo: So in the ſtate of ſeparated Spirits with Chriſt; ſo in the Kingdom of Chriſt, when it is granted to the <hi>Lamb's Wife</hi> to be <hi>arrayed</hi> in <hi>Linnen white,</hi> and <hi>clean</hi> which <hi>is the Righteouſneſs of the Saints,</hi> Rev. 19. and to each Saint to appear in <hi>Robes waſhed white in the Blood of the Lamb.</hi> And ſo in the Kingdom of Eternity, <hi>Deliver'd up to God all in all;</hi> And Leave is given to the <hi>Preachers</hi> of the Goſpel to deſcribe things, as in God's Eternity, and if not to ſpeak the moſt in number, yet the moſt important and ſignificant of Scripture words: For why ſhould we keep our ſelves and hearers ſo cloſe muffled up in this thick Atmoſphere of time,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102302:7"/> and not let out more into the open Air of Eternals? This ſtifles and ſmothers nobler Thoughts and Elevations of Mind, and the lofty Conſiderations for Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, as well as Conſolation.</p>
               <p>But to go on further; The Sins of Believers were in the <hi>fulneſs of Time</hi> moſt conſpicuouſly laid upon Chriſt, as it was an Act of God in Time; as the very Nature of the <hi>fulneſs of Time</hi> may aſſure us; but it is true, they were in proper ſenſes laid upon Chriſt before, as he was a <hi>Lamb ſlain from the Foundation of the World,</hi> and as his <hi>Blood</hi> was the <hi>Blood</hi> of the <hi>Everlaſting Covenant;</hi> and ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably, when he was born in ſo low and mean an appearance, who had as the <hi>Eternal Word,</hi> Right to have appear'd all in glory; yet ſtill Let the <hi>fulneſs of Time have its pre-eminence;</hi> And ſo ſure there can be no injury done, when all the <hi>Aerumnae,</hi> the Sorrows of the Life of our Redeemer meet there.</p>
               <p>I go on: That Jeſus Chriſt was not abhorr'd by the Father, is moſt true; For if there could be a difference, he was; even while he <hi>bore our Sins</hi> (for then he was in the higheſt act of Self-reſignation and Obedience) above any time, <hi>the Son, in whom he was well pleaſed;</hi> yet that he was <hi>made a Curſe;</hi> that the <hi>Lord bruiſed him</hi> and <hi>put him to grief;</hi> that he look'd like a Man <hi>ſmitten of God;</hi> that God loathing and abhorring the ſins, with which he was loaden, would not ſhew himſelf to him; but that, <hi>He cried out, My God, my God, why haſt thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken me,</hi> is alſo moſt true; In that <hi>Oeconomy</hi> or Diſpenſation Chriſt ſtood under the Imputation of the Sins of all the <hi>Elect;</hi> which Sin God hates: whoever therefore <hi>bears Sin,</hi> muſt bear that Abhorrence of God, Sin draws upon it ſelf, till he hath purg'd it off. Thus Chriſt did, till He had overcome it; therefore he ſtood bearing, that God abhorr'd; and ſo muſt bear ſuch an Abhorrence as the Sins deſerved. Chriſt, under the multitude of our Sins, was ſo cover'd, that, as, I may ſay with reverence, <hi>He could not look up,</hi> ſo he could not be ſeen; the Sins then, wherewith he was ſo compaſs'd, drew Abhorrence, as upon himſelf. And I know not what difference there is between Chriſt <hi>made a Curſe,</hi> and as <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horr'd of God;</hi> whatever explains and reconciles the one to our thoughts, will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile the other alſo. And in no other ſenſe, can a ſober and good Man be thought to ſpeak it. And ſo underſtood, it hath its great Scripture-Uſe, to ſhew us, how truly and really Chriſt hath by his Death devour'd all that Curſe, Hatred, and Abhorrence due to us for Sin, by expiating it in himſelf: For if it had not in that Diſpenſation been upon him, he had not fully and effectually aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd its Abolition; we may humbly imitate Scripture in ſo ſpeaking, while we yet know Chriſt was always <hi>the beloved Son.</hi> This ſhews alſo Sin's hateful Nature.</p>
               <p>I ſtill go on: Chriſt taking us as his Members, whatever unworthineſs we have, muſt redound upon him, ſo, as that he hath reaſon to diſcharge himſelf of it; and ſo to attone his Members: And what is His, is ſo far his Members, each one in particular, as is neceſſary to us, as Members: But ſo is not his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatorial Righteouſneſs, nor his Perfection of Holineſs. No word of which <hi>Mediatorial Righteouſneſs</hi> I find cited; but that Exchange of Perſons and Perfection of Holineſs ariſing from it, are only exuberant Repreſentatives of two great Truths. 1. That our Sins were fully and perfectly taken by Chriſt upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and expiated in himſelf; For by his <hi>Sacrifice for Sin,</hi> he <hi>condemned Sin in</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:102302:8"/> 
                  <hi>the Fleſh, viz.</hi> in his own Humane Nature; And that his Righteouſneſs is ſo ours by his communication of it, as to his Members, <hi>Fleſh of his Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>Bone of his Bone,</hi> and one <hi>Spirit with him;</hi> that there is, and was as it were real Exchange of Perſons. There is; For the True Believer by ſuch a Reception into Chriſt is changed into that Righteous Perſon, he is made by Chriſt, and is, as in him. There was; For Chriſt in the very Act of Expiation, did as it were put on the ſinful Perſon of every Believer, <hi>made Sin for them.</hi> Why ſhould we be afraid to uſe ſuch Full Sounds as Scripture hath done, however reduced by Interpretation to the <hi>Analogy of Faith?</hi> Sure it ſanctified ſuch Sounds as it made. And how great Exundancies of Expreſſion are found, and not blamed in the beſt of the Ancient Fathers? and had they not been preſs'd beyond their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, had ſweeten'd and made acceptable greateſt Truths to Hearers and Readers; Had no Monſtrous and Portentous Conſequences been rais'd from them; The Debtor and Surety paying the Debt, change perſons; ſo does the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; Chriſt is made our Sin, and a Curſe for us. The Church <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is called the <hi>Lord our Righteouſneſs,</hi> Jer. 33. 16. even as Chriſt himſelf, <hi>c.</hi> 23. 6. which however, I know is otherwiſe rendred, yet is moſt naturally and eaſily ſo to be underſtood: Even as <hi>Jehovah, Shamah,</hi> Ezek. <hi>ult.</hi> Which comes very near a Concionatory or Popular Aſcribing the Mediatorial Righteouſneſs of Chriſt to Believers: Maſſy Truths will endure to be beaten out ſo into Leaf Gold, while the Solid Bulk is preſerv'd ſafe in Doctrinal <hi>Forms of Sound Words:</hi> Thus Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, repreſenting the mighty Powers of Divine Action and Providence in God, aſcribes to him the Parts of Body, by which Men act, ſo well known to them: Yet let no Men from hence <hi>Dogmatize,</hi> as the <hi>Anthropomorphites,</hi> that God is Corporeal; No more, that Chriſt was indeed a Sinner, or <hi>Accurſed,</hi> or that Believers are Saviours, and Mediators one to another; For ſo, there would be none to be ſaved, except Chriſt himſelf by his own ſaved, and redeemed; which who can believe, any one not <hi>Phrenetic</hi> would aſſert?</p>
               <p>To conclude theſe Heads. It is moſt evident, that the Debate concerning the Perfection of Holineſs in Believers can only reſt here; Whether the Holineſs of Chriſt may not be imputed to make up the Imperfection of our Sanctification, which is indeed, but the ſame thing, with the Imputation of the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt; and ſo that in regard of the Imputation of the Holineſs of Chriſt to Believers, they may be ſaid to be Holy, as Chriſt is Holy; of which was ſpoken in the laſt Head: And that Perfection of Holineſs can be no otherwiſe meant, is moſt undeniable by the whole ſtream of Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi>'s Diſcourſe, and Mr. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liams</hi> his Objection; particularly in that part of Dr <hi>Criſp,</hi> concerning Goſpel-Marks, which he argues againſt upon the Imperfection of Sanctification, and therefore could in no other ſenſe think Believers holy, as Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="head">
               <head>Head 8.</head>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">The <hi>Covenant of Grace</hi> hath no Condition, to which is oppos'd; The <hi>Covenant of Grace</hi> hath Conditions, though undertaken for, aſſur'd, ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to, by Chriſt.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Conciliation.</label> If we conſider the Covenant of Grace, as it is in its higheſt, nobleſt Repreſentation, it is an <hi>Ectype</hi> or Exemplification of the <hi>Everlaſting Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> the <hi>Covenant</hi> in <hi>Election;</hi> and therein it muſt needs be, as unconditioned,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:102302:8"/> as <hi>Election</hi> is, and yet, as univerſally Wiſe and Holy, as the whole Scripture Frame is, even ſo Wiſe and Holy is the <hi>Counſel of that Will</hi> in <hi>Election,</hi> that <hi>God worketh all things after,</hi> Epheſ. 1. 11. More Self-conſiſtent is therefore the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis or Scheme of a Conditionate <hi>Election,</hi> and a <hi>Conditionate Covenant of Grace,</hi> then an Inconditionate <hi>Election,</hi> and a Conditional <hi>Covenant of Grace;</hi> except we make the Series and Frame of the conſequent Diſpoſes of <hi>Election</hi> Conditions, God puts upon himſelf for the making good his firſt Choice; that is, he chooſes upon Condition, he himſelf will in time give Faith, Repentance, Holineſs; which we know, were both unreaſonably derogatory from the Divine Glory; and from that order, in which Scripture gives us theſe Supreme Acts of Grace; For <hi>Foreknowledge, Predeſtination, Election,</hi> in Chriſt, are the Fountain of <hi>Calling, Juſtification, Sanctification, Glorification,</hi> Rom. 8. 29. Whereas if <hi>Sanctification</hi> were the condition of <hi>Juſtification, Glorification</hi> coming laſt muſt be the condition of all the reſt; As if the Senſe were on condition God will <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie,</hi> he will <hi>Sanctifie.</hi> So <hi>Juſtification</hi> muſt be the condition of <hi>Calling,</hi> and <hi>Calling of Election.</hi> But how much more Beautiful and Orderly is the Scripture Chain? Making all after, Wiſe diſpoſes flowing from the Independent Firſt. And ſo every where Scripture Diſcourſes; he hath choſen us, that <hi>we ſhould be Holy, and without Blame before him in Love,</hi> Epheſ. 1. As, <hi>of God,</hi> viz. by the Eternal Fountain of Grace and in his <hi>Electing</hi> Love, are <hi>we in Christ, who is of God,</hi> 1. Cor. 1. 31. without any condition on our part, made <hi>Wiſdom</hi> in <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; Righteouſneſs</hi> in <hi>Juſtification;</hi> Holyneſs in <hi>Sanctification;</hi> All theſe are brought into Glory in <hi>Redemption;</hi> that none might <hi>Glory in his Preſence,</hi> but <hi>he that Glorieth might Glory only in the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For if there were but one Thing ſuſpended upon us, as a Condition on our Part; even that ſingle thing would turn the <hi>Covenant of Grace</hi> into a <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Works;</hi> For it would be <hi>Work</hi> done by our ſelves, and we might <hi>Glory,</hi> we have done, we have <hi>will'd,</hi> we <hi>have run,</hi> we have atchiev'd and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd; what ever indeed that might be Duly demanded of us, and is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, is <hi>Grace;</hi> or whatever is given, is Grace; But what is required on our own Strength, is <hi>Work;</hi> and though it be ſaid, God aſſiſts by his Grace, by his Spirit; yet if there be 99 Parts given or aſſiſted, and but the 100th Part our Act, that 100th Part is <hi>Work,</hi> and all Grace is ſuſpended on that; For on the doing, or not doing that, All hangs: And ſeeing thouſands do not that 100th Part, if we do it, we have reaſon of Boaſting, that we were wiſer, we were better than they. For how ſmall, how little ſoever that nice and curious Point be, on which all the vaſt Globes, of not only Eternity, but Supreme <hi>Grace</hi> turns; and wherein Divine Wiſdom and Holyneſs placed all; That is ours, and we have done it. And though in all elſe, we are beholden to God, to Chriſt, to the Divine Spirit, yet in that which is the laſt Hinge we are beholden to our ſelves; Nay if all were firſt given, and but our Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance only were the Condition on which all depended, the ſame might be ſaid of Perſeverance, that it turn'd the <hi>Covenant of Grace</hi> in that Part into a <hi>Covenant of Works.</hi> And whereas many do not Perſevere, we have reaſon to <hi>Glory</hi> we Perſevere, and there is ſome thing we have not received. And ſo the Vertical
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102302:9"/> Point would be our ſelves, and we might <hi>Glory in his Preſence:</hi> For that, and not Chriſt, would be the <hi>Corner Stone,</hi> and to it we might cry, <hi>Grace, Grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And however, there is ſo much to be aſcrib'd to Grace, and what would in common Speaking, among Men, be call'd the making of us, and doing all for us; Yet it is to be conſider'd, whether the <hi>Glory,</hi> God will <hi>not give to another,</hi> be not parted with, and ſurrendred by him, if the laſt Deciſive Point Reſt upon us; which makes me Aſſured, it cannot be ſo; And ſo though I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge with thoſe, who moſt acknowledge it; the neceſſity of Faith, Repentance, Holyneſs, and of our own Action therein; yet in ſpeaking of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> as the <hi>Covenant of Grace,</hi> and being an <hi>Ectype,</hi> or Exemplification of <hi>Everlaſting Grace;</hi> I ſay, Theſe, nor any Action of the <hi>Elect,</hi> ought to be ſtyled Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but Wiſe and Holy Diſpoſitions of God the Author and Founder; and of Chriſt the <hi>Mediator, Surety</hi> and <hi>Teſtator;</hi> And which he will moſt certainly ſee to, that they ſhall moſt Infallibly take place in their juſt Series, Succeſſion and Order both of Nature and of Time.</p>
               <p>And why ſhould we be ſo afraid to ſpeak of the Covenant of Grace, as Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionate? For what is there that we would ſingle out as a condition, that is not to be aſcrib'd to Gods Immediate Gift? Is it Faith? Is it <hi>the Gift of God?</hi> Epheſ. 2. 8. To you <hi>Is it given to believe?</hi> Is it <hi>Repentance? He hath made Chriſt a Prince to give it,</hi> Acts 5. 31. <hi>If God peradventure will give Repentance,</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 25. Is it Holyneſs? Chriſt is made ſo <hi>Sanctification</hi> to us that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>Boaſt;</hi> Is it the <hi>Laws of God in our Hearts, A new Heart, a new Spirit, a ſoft Heart, his Fear within us,</hi> that <hi>we may never depart from him? One Heart,</hi> and <hi>one Way to fear him forever, to know him by his Spirit?</hi> All theſe are aſſurd to be given, even as Pardon in Sin, and by as free a Gift. All by a plain abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Inconditionate Grant; How many and great Scriptures run in this abſolute Style, and yet how expreſly is all this call'd a Covenant? <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. <hi>Jer.</hi> 32. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 11. Chap. 36.</p>
               <p>But if it be ſaid, how then comes it to paſs, that the whole Strain and Stream of Scripture, to which Preaching ought to be conform'd, ſpeaks of theſe Graces and all the Actions agreeable to them, as Conditions of the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace?</hi> There are three grand Accounts to be given of it.</p>
               <p n="1">I. It becomes the Wiſe and Holy Rector and Governor of the World and of his Rational Human Creation, to treat and deal with, and give them all Scope, Room and Buſineſs, and Advantage in, and for Intellectual Action; Men, as Rational Creatures, know not how to deal with one another, or to move themſelves, but by the Activities of Underſtanding, Conſcience, Will, Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; So that they muſt lye ſtill, and not act at all, or be moov'd only, as Bruits or Machines, or thus; There is therefore the continual Rational Breathing, and Motion of Doctrine, <hi>Inſtruction, Promiſe, Threat, Reproof, Correction;</hi> and all kind of Motion and Action, ſuitable and agreeable to it: <hi>All Scripture</hi> is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore prepared, and <hi>Profitable</hi> hereunto. Beſides the Commands and Precepts of Holyneſs being ſo abundant, they ſhew the neceſſity of a continual Recourſe to Chriſt for Strength, Grace and Aſſiſtance, for Righteouſneſs from him, and Pardon through him, wherein we fall ſhort; Nothing mooves more to run
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102302:9"/> to the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, than the ſight of Imperfect Grace and Action, to which we are called; if by our ſelves; though under Divine Aſſiſtance from Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Now under this Oeconomy, and Diſpenſation of Things; the Grace of God, according to Election, and according to the <hi>Mediation, Suretyſhip</hi> and <hi>Teſtamentary Grace</hi> (or the laſt Will of Jeſus Chriſt) diſplay themſelves; as if all things were carryed by Intellectual Conditionalities, and the Obedience and free Complyances of thoſe who are the <hi>Election of God,</hi> of thoſe, that are <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led according to Purpoſe;</hi> while in the mean time, they are moſt Efficaciouſly, and yet moſt ſweetly Swayed, and Influenc'd by the Power and Grace of God in Chriſt, and by the Increated Spirit, that cannot miſs of the end deſign'd; and though all be Veſted in the Action of thoſe, who are thus <hi>Choſen</hi> and <hi>Called,</hi> yet not under the Incertainty of a Condition; but the Infallible Certainty of a Divine Diſpoſition, a Teſtamentary Gift of our great <hi>Teſtator,</hi> a Diſcharge of our <hi>Surety</hi> for us, though within us; an Acquiſt of our <hi>Mediator</hi> by Interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on his own Blood of the Everlaſting <hi>Covenant,</hi> preſented in <hi>Heaven for us,</hi> Heb. 9 12.</p>
               <p n="3">III. And thus alſo, there is a Juſtification of God in his Holyneſs and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, as alſo in his <hi>Patience</hi> and <hi>Long Suffering</hi> towards thoſe, whom he leaves to themſelves; who being applyed to, according to their own Nature, as Creatures of Reaſon and Underſtanding, according to all the Riches of the Word of God to that purpoſe, are condemned in not receiving ſuch every way ſufficient Applications, taking them ſo every way, as ſuch Rational Creatures, and ſuited thereunto; which could not be ſo gloriouſly Demonſtrated and Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated, if there were not ſuch a fittedneſs of the Word of God, and of the Overtures of Life and Salvation, by way of Condition. To one, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 11. it is given, to the other, it is not given. So <hi>vain</hi> is that Expoſition of Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> and violent a <hi>Perverſion</hi> of Scripture; As <hi>many as were ordain'd,</hi> viz. as he ſpeaks, fitted by former Diſcipline to receive the <hi>Eternal Life</hi> of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. <hi>ult. believed:</hi> As appears from, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 23. For what Diſcipline prepared beforehand the <hi>Gentiles</hi> to Calling or Glory?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="head">
               <head>Head 9.</head>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Faith is not an Aſſurance or Inward Perſuaſion that Chriſt is ours, and that our Sins are Pardon'd; But it is Accepting, Receiving and Reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon Chriſt alone for Juſtification.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Conciliation.</label> That Faith is a Grace of a moſt large and ſpreading Nature and Action, as it is repreſented to us in the Word of God, can be by no one, that conſiders it, denyed. So that there may be many Excellent and Profitable Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes upon it, that may look very diſtantly one upon another, and yet meet in the iame Center: Yet Faith as it reſpects Pardon of Sin, and Juſtification, cannot have a fairer and fuller Propoſition given it, than that <hi>ſaying, Worthy of both Belief</hi> or full Aſſent of the Judgment, and <hi>Acceptation</hi> of the Will, <hi>viz.</hi> that Chriſt came to <hi>ſave the chief of Sinners,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1, 15. Now this Propoſition every one is to particularize to himſelf, as the Apoſtles, in believing; and ſo it differs nothing from Aſſurance, in the Root at leaſt; And that, Aſſurance is every way moſt Connatural to it, is evident by the Apoſtles ſpeaking of the <hi>full</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:102302:10"/> 
                  <hi>Aſſurance of Knowledge,</hi> Col. 2. 2. As Faith is an Intellectual Aſſent to Divine Revelation; <hi>The full Aſſurance of Faith,</hi> as it is an Application for Pardon to the <hi>Blood of Chriſt, ſprinkling the Heart from an evil Conſcience,</hi> Heb. 10. 22. and the <hi>full Aſſurance of Hope,</hi> Heb. 6. 11. as Faith concerning our preſent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts in Chriſt not yet appearing fully, or in future Glory; aides it ſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt preſent low Appearances of its pardon'd juſtify'd State, or its future Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Thus a <hi>Plerophory</hi> or <hi>full Aſſurance</hi> in relation to Faith, cannot merit any Indignation, as againſt an Error; And indeed it is ſo eſſential to Faith, that there never was nor can be any true Faith without the Root, and Seed of it; and the Letting it down in the Deſcriptions and Diſcourſes of it from this full Aſſurance is in compaſſion to the low State; Tempted, Deſerted, Afflicted, Doubting State, of ſincere Chriſtians; It was the general Doctrin of the firſt <hi>Reformers,</hi> when the Light was pureſt and quickeſt.</p>
               <p>And it is very ſuſpitionable, the Letting it down lower may have had its Ill, as well as its good Effects; For if Chriſtians aim'd in all their ways at full Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, it would engage them to higher Aims in Holyneſs, and cloſer Walking; It being impoſſible even in the Judgment of Natural Light and Reaſon to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Holyneſs from ſuch Aſſurance; or that receiving Chriſt, as Lord and King, ſhould be made to part from it, but that it would flow out into all Expreſſions of the Warmeſt and Indearedſt Love to him. Whereas Chriſtians Reſting and thinking it a piece of Modeſty and Humility (it were well, if it were not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyed to that <hi>Voluntary Humility</hi> ſpoken of, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 18.) to be in doubt, and only flatly and deadly to hope well in general, They find not theſe pungent Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to move Accurate and Univerſal Obedience; but poize the one to the other, their Obedience to their Meaſure of Aſſurance. For a rude Preſumption or bold Saying, Chriſt is ours, and our Sins are pardon'd in the midſt of Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and looſe Living, is worthy only to be exploded, and Hiſſed off the very Profeſſion of Chriſtianity; and cannot obtain the leaſt Credit, either with others or even the Rational Conſcience in themſelves. So that were it not in Tenderneſs to the Weakneſs of Chriſtians in general; Preaching Faith ſo, as to include Aſſurance in it, would be undoubtedly the beſt; and even that taken care of, as well, as it may be; I know not whether it might not be much to the Intereſt and Glory of Chriſtianity, to wind it up in the moſt ſtated Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of Faith to the Apoſtles <hi>Plerophory;</hi> or <hi>full A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>urance</hi> of <hi>Knowledge, Faith</hi> and <hi>Hope;</hi> from which Exceptions might be made, and Allowances for the Weakneſs of Chriſtians in particular Exigencies. This ſure would more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble Chriſtianity. It was the Illuſtrious State of the very Primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, which we read of in that moſt admirable part of <hi>Church Hiſtory,</hi> the five firſt Chapters of the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles;</hi> To this I doubt not, it will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd within few Years, when in the <hi>Succeſſion of the Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> and by the Proclaiming, <hi>The Kingdoms of this World are the Kingdoms of the Lord and of his Christ,</hi> Rev. 11. 15. The Servants of God ſhall <hi>appear on Mount</hi> Zion <hi>with the Lamb,</hi> having the <hi>Fathers Name,</hi> not Sealed under Reſerve, as yet it is; but <hi>Written</hi> in Capital Letters, in ſplendid Characters <hi>on their Foreheads.</hi> It is the <hi>dark and foul place of the Apoſtacy,</hi> 2 Pet 1. 19. in which we are (the Beaſts <hi>forty two Months,</hi> being though near, yet not fully expired) <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. 5. that brings ſo low the Doctrin of Faith, as being not Aſſurance.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:102302:10"/>
               <p> And becauſe in the Reformation begun Chriſt appear'd, making his Challenge of his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and the <hi>ſeven Thunders</hi> of higheſt Goſpel Doctrin <hi>uttered their Voices,</hi> Rev. 10. (A Chapter, on purpoſe, to give us the Prophetick Landskip of the <hi>Reformation.)</hi> There was the high Doctrin of Faith, as Aſſurance; Yet theſe <hi>Thunders being ſcal'd,</hi> (now near again to be <hi>unſeal'd)</hi> It flatted again, as now we ſee: And this is the Reaſon, the Diſcourſes of Aſſurance, as ſo eſſential to Faith, are almoſt as Portentous, as the Doctrin of the Kingdom of Chriſt in ſuch a near appearing Glory, and any Aſpiring to it, as preſumptuous.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="head">
               <head>Head 10.</head>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Prevailing Enmity is no hindrance to our Intereſt in Chriſt.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Conciliation.</label> This may be apprehended three ways, and be very great truth.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Elect Sinner, in the midſt of the moſt prevailing Enmity, hath ſuch Intereſt in Chriſt; that his Reſcue from Sin, Hell, and Death, is ſo ſecur'd and depoſited by the Divine Decree for him in Chriſt; that the very height of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity ſhall not diſintereſt him, but Chriſt will break through that Enmity, and ſeize upon him, even when it is moſt Boiling up and Raging: Thus <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 9. being a <hi>choſen Veſſel,</hi> even while he had a Knife in his hand to murther Chriſt, had yet ſuch an Intereſt in Chriſt, by that <hi>Electing Grace,</hi> that his Converſion, Faith, Repentance and Apoſtleſhip lay treaſur'd up in Chriſt; and Chriſt had ſuch an Intereſt in him, That an <hi>Everlaſting Arm</hi> was about him, and he was <hi>Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended</hi> by Chrſt for <hi>that very Thing,</hi> that in Due Time he might by Faith <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend Christ.</hi> And ſurely this is an Intereſt of no mean account.</p>
               <p n="2">2. At the very height of Enmity the chiefeſt Sinner hath that Intereſt in Chriſt, that he may come and apprehend Chriſt by Faith, and receive all the Benefits of Chriſt; and the very firſt of thoſe Benefits ſhall be the Healing him of that En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity: He hath a Right to <hi>come;</hi> If it be ſaid, Enmity and Coming connot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt; it is true; But his preſent Enmity does not diſintereſt him in a Right to <hi>come,</hi> if he would; But it hinders his being willing to <hi>come;</hi> Yet in the moment the Grace of Chriſt <hi>Abounds</hi> to the <hi>Elect</hi> Perſon at the Appointed Time with <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> which are in Chriſt Jeſus, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 14. Preſent Enmity is no more hindrance to an Intereſt in Chriſt, but that, as in <hi>Paul,</hi> it falls flat, in what moment that <hi>Grace</hi> pleaſes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To win upon Sinners to <hi>come</hi> to Chriſt, it may be ſaid to them, while in the Preaching of the Goſpel, there is a Probing, or Endeavouring to Find out the <hi>Elect,</hi> and Bring them to Chriſt; It may be, I ſay, ſaid to them; Come, though you have the higheſt Enmity, That is no hindrance to your Intereſt in Chriſt, ſuppoſed you <hi>come;</hi> For in that very moment, you turn to <hi>come to Chriſt,</hi> your Enmity ſhall drop off from you: It is a Hindrance to the preſent Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Intereſt, not to the Intereſt it ſelf; that is ſecur'd in Electing Grace, and the Free Promiſes of the Goſpel, intended, and deſign'd for all the Elect. And this the Goſpel gives right to the Preachers of it to declare; But the doubt, whether this, or that particular Perſon belongs to that <hi>Election,</hi> while he is in Enmity; and the certainty of Enmity ceaſing in the very coming; is as a drawn Sword between a claim of Intereſt in Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and perſervering Enmity.</p>
               <p>If it be ſaid, There muſt be <hi>Humiliation, Wearin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſs, Sight of Sin,</hi> and <hi>Sorrow</hi> for it. The Methods of <hi>Electing Grace,</hi> that it hath preſcribed to it ſelf, will take
<pb facs="tcp:102302:11"/> care for all; and ſo that all ſuch Affections and Acts ſhall be rais'd up, excited, and carried on in the Sinner himſelf, and even by himſelf under the Efficacy of that Grace: And thus underſtood, as it muſt be, except he that ſpeaks ſo, be a perſon void of all Holy Senſe, or ſo much as Sober (and ſuch Dr <hi>Criſp</hi> was not in the Judgment of Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> as appears in the laſt Lines of the Preface) They muſt therefore be underſtood to be ſpoken by way of earneſt perſwaſion to <hi>come</hi> to Chriſt; and to Eſſay upon Men, by propoſing the Largeſt and Freeſt Terms; So the Miniſters of Chriſt, as <hi>Fiſhers,</hi> ſpread the <hi>Net,</hi> to <hi>Catch Men;</hi> As Scripture ſays, he hath <hi>received Gifts for the Rebellious alſo,</hi> that the <hi>Lord God may dwell among them,</hi> Pſal. 68. 18. And as <hi>Abraham</hi> is ſaid, to <hi>Believe on Him, that Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifies the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly:</hi> Why may not the moſt expatiating Expreſſions be uſed in ſo good a Senſe, and with ſo good a Deſign, ſeeing Scripture hath us'd ſuch? And why may not as good an Effect be hop'd for from this way of Speaking, ſeeing Scripture hath us'd it, as from the ſeverer ways Scripture hath alſo us'd, according to the variety of <hi>Gifts</hi> and <hi>Motions</hi> of the ſame Spirit, and both be bleſſed by God giving effect through Chriſt?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="head">
               <head>Head 11.</head>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">The Elect are not united to Chriſt, without Faith; Upon Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving only we are related to Chriſt, as all the Metaphors of Union import.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Conciliation.</label> The being <hi>choſen in Christ before the World began, being predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Adoption of Children</hi> by Jeſus Chriſt to himſelf, cannot be without Union; The firſt Powers of <hi>Regeneration, Converſion, Softneſs of Heart, Contriteneſs of Spirit, Faith, Repentance,</hi> which the Apoſtle expreſſes by <hi>Wiſdom</hi> or <hi>Calling, in Christ Jeſus,</hi> cannot be without Union; And yet it is true, that ſetled Union of Communion, or Union of Communion, cannot be, till Chriſt be received by the Faith of <hi>God's Elect;</hi> nor can the Elect be at all known to themſelves from the Non-Elect. So that as there is need of all the <hi>Forcible</hi> and <hi>Right Words</hi> of Scripture, to ſhew; without Faith, Repentance, Holineſs, there can be no U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Communion with Chriſt, or of the Conſolation ariſing from it; even according to the Eternal <hi>Counſel of Him,</hi> that <hi>worketh all Things after the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of his own Will;</hi> So on the other ſide, there is Authority and Warrant to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that Inſeparable Union between the <hi>Head of the Adoption,</hi> and all that are <hi>Predeſtinated to the Adoption of Children in Him;</hi> that it may be acknowledg'd to the <hi>Praiſe of the Glory of his Grace,</hi> who hath laid his Foundation ſo ſure; And it may be alſo Declar'd by way of Invitation and Encouragement in <hi>coming</hi> to Chriſt; that Sinners, who look towards him, may be begotten; an effect; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are wholly paſſive; to a living Hope, through his Grace; who does it of his own Will; and yet by the <hi>Word of Truth</hi> in all parts of it, as a ſubordinate Miniſtry; and that they may be invited to look towards him, and that they may be encourag'd to expect Grace from Chriſt for Union of Communion, flowing from the Union of the <hi>Predeſtinated Adoption in Him,</hi> at the juſt time appointed by God for it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="heads">
               <head>Head.</head>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">That of Juſtification before Faith hath been already ſpoken to, but I will add ſomething to it on the next Head.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Head 12.</label> Repentance is neceſſary to Pardon.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Conciliation.</label> Seeing <hi>Juſtification</hi> and <hi>Pardon</hi> include neceſſarily the Removals of
<pb facs="tcp:102302:11"/> the Wrath and Diſpleaſure of God in all the dreadful Effects of it; and alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note as neceſſarily the Breaking out of his Favour in the moſt gracious Effects of it; how Faith or Repentance can be perfectly or in full ſenſe before either <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification</hi> or <hi>Pardon,</hi> but that mighty Rays and Beams of each muſt be broken out to the Soul, before it enters into the Beginnings of Eternal Life by Faith and Repentance; is very hard to underſtand; except Faith and Repentance are aſcrib'd to Man, as the Products of his own Power and Will. If they are from God, his Juſtifying Righteouſneſs and Pardon are come near, when-ever, where-ever he gives Faith and Repentance; And as it may be moſt neceſſary in ſome regards to Preach Faith and Repentance, as in order to Pardon and Juſtification; ſo is it no leſs neceſſary to be as Free, and Large, that without graciouſeſt Approaches of the Righteouſneſs of God and Chriſt brought near, Faith and Repentance lye for ever dead; that every unconverted Perſon may gaſp up to God and Chriſt for that Grace, that is <hi>abundant</hi> in Him. The intention is not, that <hi>Pardon</hi> or <hi>Juſtification</hi> can be without Faith or Repentance, but whether <hi>Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> doth not draw and excite its own <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Pardon,</hi> its own <hi>Repentance;</hi> So that they are rather before Faith and Repentance, than Faith and Repentance before them: And which Preaching is moſt to be preferr'd in the Nature of Things, without reſpect to the <hi>Preſent Neceſſity,</hi> and for the <hi>Time Being;</hi> That which is moſt abundant in aſcribing to the Principal, or in preſſing the Leſs Principal, and Subordinate; I make no doubt, the Singing the new Song, before ſpoken of, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. will in a ſhort time determine. And yet I defer all, that ought to be deferr'd, to thoſe whoſe Spirits are both enlarg'd and enabled to offer to the Souls of Men, the things wherein God appears, as the Rector of the World offering Faith and Repentance, in order to <hi>Juſtification</hi> and <hi>Pardon;</hi> while the Secret Springs of his <hi>Juſtifying</hi> and <hi>Pardoning Grace</hi> give the very Faith and Repentance required. But ſurely great reſpect may be had to what is to be, without violating what is, even as <hi>Sacrifices</hi> are debas'd, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 1. in foreſight of their final removal by Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="head">
               <head>Head 13.</head>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Sinners have much to do to be ſaved.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Conciliation.</label> Even the <hi>Righteous arc ſcarcely ſaved;</hi> For <hi>with Men it's impoſſible, but with God all things are poſſible. I can do all things through Chriſt ſtrengthening me; My Yoke</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>is eaſie, my Burden is light; I will run the way of thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments when Thou ſhall enlarge my Heart. The Joy of the Lord is Strength. His Delight is in the Law of the Lord; Faithful is he that hath Promiſed, and will Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it to the Day of Jeſus Chriſt; Great and Precious Promiſes are given, whereby we are made Partakers of the Divine Nature; We can do nothing againſtſt the Truth, but for the Truth.</hi> All theſe, with innumerable more of the like, ſhew the Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty and the Eaſineſs of the Salvation of <hi>God's Elect.</hi> And yet as we look to Man, and his Motion and Action, theſe Things are impoſſible: For there is no doubt Holineſs and New Obedience are the Paths wherein, though, with many Imperfections Falls and weakneſſes in the preſent ſtate, God carries his Elect to Life and Salvation; And <hi>the Way</hi> is <hi>narrow,</hi> and the <hi>Gate ſtrait,</hi> and require <hi>ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> to <hi>Enter;</hi> But <hi>God is their ſtrength,</hi> who <hi>keeps their Foot from being taken, that they walk in their way ſafely,</hi> and <hi>their Steps are not ſtraitned; He makes their Feet as</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:102302:12"/> 
                  <hi>Hinds Feet;</hi> and <hi>ſets them on High Places. They that wait on the Lord run, and are not weary; They walk and faint not. He girdeth them with ſtrength: By him they leap over a Wall.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14-15" type="head">
               <head>Head 14, 15.</head>
               <p>I joyn theſe Two together. <q rend="margQuotes">The Goſpel hath Threats and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; Holineſs and Good Works are neceſſary to Salvation.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Conciliation.</label> As upon the gracious Councels of God before <hi>All Worlds</hi> Began; ſo upon this very Point, among all the Diſpoſes of God in time; the Hinge of theſe Points turns; For if the Goſpel be a Law full of all Holy and Righteous Precepts, to which Faith and Repentance introduce us; arm'd with its Promiſes and Threats, and ſo ſetled as a Covenant; that who of himſelf accepts the Terms of it by Faith and Repentance, under the Aſſurance of the Aſſiſtances of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Spirit, are accepted, and ſhall have All the Benefits of it; and whoever will not ſhall be <hi>Damn'd,</hi> and his Judgment ſhall be more intollerable, becauſe he refuſes ſuch gracious Terms offerr'd: This doth, I confeſs, perfectly overthrow Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi>'s Scheme; For then Chriſt comes in as a <hi>Law-giver,</hi> and having all <hi>Judgment committed to him;</hi> and there is a <hi>Mediatorian Law</hi> and <hi>Covenant</hi> in the <hi>Hand of the Mediator,</hi> of more gracious condeſcention than that of the Covenant of Works; but the laſt reſult of all is into the free Will of Man, and his Action in compliance with this <hi>Covenant;</hi> Thus of the <hi>Law,</hi> and the <hi>Covonant of Works,</hi> as the Firſt <hi>Law,</hi> there is a Perfect Abrogation as a Law; but as the Holineſs and Righteouſneſs of it are tranſplanted into this New Law; ſo here is, as to that Law, a perfect <hi>Antinomianiſm;</hi> and all Mankind are only under this <hi>Law;</hi> and <hi>Juſtification, Salvation,</hi> or <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Condemnation,</hi> are according to Obedience or Diſobedience to this Law or <hi>Goſpel-Covenant,</hi> of which the Conditions are Faith and Repentance. But if the Goſpel in the Supreme Intention of it, and in the Propriety of its Nature, be a <hi>Covenant of Grace,</hi> wherein God is pleas'd to be from his own free <hi>purpoſe of Grace</hi> the Soveraign <hi>Covenantee;</hi> and his <hi>Elect</hi> bear the <hi>Analogy,</hi> or part of <hi>Covenantees,</hi> as at the other Extreme; and Jeſus Chriſt the <hi>Mediator, Surety,</hi> and <hi>Teſtator,</hi> paſs between both, that all may be perform'd, <hi>Mediating</hi> with God for his efficacious Grace, in giving the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Diſpoſitions promiſed in this Covenant, as if perform'd by the Covenantees; So bringing every thing in effect from God to us, and from us to God; and by his Death having right as a <hi>Teſtator</hi> to beſtow the very things upon All, <hi>given to him by God</hi> to <hi>give Eternal Life to them,</hi> John 17. 2. Then ſhall the Goſpel, or <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> be ſupremely a <hi>Miniſtration of the Spirit, of Righteouſneſs, of Life,</hi> according to 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>And in its Subordinate Nature, it ſhall be a Publication of the Divine Grace and Love to Mankind in general, upon the Terms of Faith and Repentance.</p>
               <p>The Law all this time ſtands in its own place, as the Eternal Sanction of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and Righteouſneſs, and can never be abrogated; becauſe it is Eternal Righteouſneſs; but it is as a <hi>Covenant</hi> ſo far mitigated, as to accept the Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction it requires from a <hi>Mediator;</hi> and ſo it is <hi>in the Hand of a Mediator,</hi> Gal. 3. 19. Towards whom it commands Faith, and Repentance, or return to God by him; even as it is a Law of Eternal Righteouſneſs, Requiring Faith and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to all Manifeſtations from God, ſufficiently teſtified to be from him; and
<pb facs="tcp:102302:12"/> as theſe Manifeſtations of Grace are the only poſſibility left to a fallen Nature to return into a State of Agreement with God.</p>
               <p>Hereupon the Law becomes a Standard, by which the full Value of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of Chriſt by his Sacrifice, and Obedience unto Juſtification, and the Infinite Grace of God in Pardon is tryed, and made glorious; by which the Duties of Humiliation, Confeſſion of Sin, Application to Chriſt for Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, Repentance, ſhould be both underſtood and urged; Here is the Rule for Holineſs and new Obedience, out of which all the Holy Precepts of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel are drawn; Hereby the Remainders of Sin are Diſcern'd, and Humiliation under them wrought: Hereby is the Infinite Grace of Chriſt towards his Legatees, his Redeemed, ſet at full Light, in working an Inward Conformity to this Holy Law in all parts of it; And hereby the Government of God, committed to Chriſt, is continued with Relation to all Mankind, even to all not given to him; For they who have the Goſpel Preached to them, are judged not only according to the Law of Righteouſneſs, firſt <hi>written in the Heart,</hi> but according to this Divine Revelation and Grace; which highly aggravates their Diſobedience, and makes it more <hi>Tollerable for Sodom and Gomorrah,</hi> than for them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 24. They who have not the Goſpel are judged according to that Law, and Light of Nature, They have concerning the Law; and that Witneſs of an Intention of Grace, God gives to them in <hi>giving Fruitful Times and Seaſons,</hi> and all the Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries of his Patience, <hi>Leading them to Repentance; even as the King of Nineveh,</hi> who ſhall riſe up in Judgment and condemn Heathens, who have not by ſuch a Light from the forbearance of God argued to Repentance, as he did: And thus are the <hi>Secrets of all Hearts,</hi> judged according to the <hi>Apoſtles Goſpel,</hi> as he ſaid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 16. Some Ombrage of which Heathens have.</p>
               <p>Thus the Law is eſtabliſhed and preſerved in its full Authority; and the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel is alſo eſtabliſh'd as Divine Revelation; and in its High, purely promiſſory Part, as a <hi>Ministration of the Spirit;</hi> And if the Deſignation of the Goſpel be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly ſingled out for the moſt powerful Preaching of it by ſome, and yet in the mean time the more large, and univerſal Motion, and Doctrin of the Goſpel be Preach'd more univerſally by the moſt of the Preachers; whom the Spirit of God, according alſo to the general Stream of Scripture, hath ſo Miſſiond, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion'd, and Enabled. I cannot ſee, but here may be the Sweeteſt Union, and as great a Conſpiration, as between the <hi>Apostle Paul,</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtle James;</hi> while one tells us a Man juſtifyed by <hi>Faith without Works;</hi> and the Laſt tells us by what of Faith, <hi>viz,</hi> not by the Body of Faith, or a Confeſſion of Faith, but by the Spirit of it, the <hi>Vis Eſſectrix</hi> or <hi>Operatrix,</hi> the working Efficacy of it; which I take on great Reaſon to be the very true Expedient of Reconciliation between the two Apoſtles; and yet in both, by the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt by Faith alone, and that Faith given only by Chriſt; So all is of Grace, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. For Faith and all its Works flow from the Blood and Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, drawing nigh to his Elect People to Regenerate, and to juſtifie together, <hi>Titus,</hi> 3. 5. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And ſurely by a cloſe and univerſal Compare of Scripture, <hi>The Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> muſt be according to this very ſame Grace; For when the Spirits of Saints
<pb facs="tcp:102302:13"/> are immediately with Chriſt; and He receives them, who Dye, and <hi>Sleep in him;</hi> in a Moment, in the Twinkling of an Eye made Perfect; and when they are <hi>Raiſed Incorruptible,</hi> he <hi>brings them with him;</hi> and they together with Chriſt, <hi>Judge Angels and the World;</hi> And it is given to them to <hi>Appear</hi> in <hi>Robes waſh'd white</hi> in the <hi>Blood of the Lamb,</hi> and to be <hi>Cloathed in Linnen white and clean,</hi> which is the <hi>Righteouſneſs of the Saints;</hi> and he preſents them to himſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Spot, Wrinckle</hi> or <hi>any ſuch Thing;</hi> It cannot be underſtood that the Day of Judgment, in relation to the Saints, is by way of Tryal of Judgment on par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Actions; But their very Appearance is their Abſolution, and Adjudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Glory, as Clad in the rich Robes, <hi>Waſh'd in the Blood of the Lamb;</hi> All their Graces, and Holy Duties fill'd up, and their <hi>Sins perfectly blotted out,</hi> and remainders of Corruption effaced by Grace perfected in Glory.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide, The wicked have Appearances in their Sins, having <hi>found them out, covering them as a Garment of Diſhonour,</hi> and as filthy Garments, that expoſe them immediately to Condemnation: And as if their particular Sins were written upon them, and the Condemnation together with them.</p>
               <p>And thus each appear viſibly before the Throne, Tribunal and Judgment Seat of Chriſt, during the whole <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> of his <hi>Kingdom;</hi> One Crowned with <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> the other cover'd with <hi>Shame</hi> and <hi>Contempt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If any ſhould object Chriſts inſiſting on the particular Duty of <hi>Viſiting, Cloathing, Feeding,</hi> Mat. 25. either as perform'd or neglected: It is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd; each ſort firſt were ſet, one on the <hi>Right Hand,</hi> the other on the <hi>Left;</hi> one as <hi>Sheep,</hi> the other as <hi>Goats:</hi> So the Tryal was eaſie.</p>
               <p>If it be further ſaid, <hi>God will bring every Work into Judgment, whether it be Good or Evil.</hi> This I attribute to the mighty Power and Wiſdom of God, giving together with every Perſon before his Judgment, all the Holy Actions of Saints <hi>waſh'd and perfected</hi> in, and by the <hi>Blood of Jeſus;</hi> and fill'd up with his <hi>Grace,</hi> and by the Spirit; as in a Moment, an <hi>Atom of Time,</hi> the <hi>Twinkling of an Eye;</hi> and their Sins ſo taken away, as not only <hi>not to be found,</hi> but not <hi>to be.</hi> Whereas the Talents of wicked Men, that is, any good Things they had here, not being purged by his Blood, perfected by his Obedience, and fill'd up by his Spirit, are taken from them, and they appear All in their Sins; And thus the Order of Things at that Day, is according to the free Grace of <hi>Election, Calling, Juſtification;</hi> and <hi>Sanctification,</hi> covered under <hi>Juſtification;</hi> in that Chain of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. and <hi>Glorification</hi> ſpringing from all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="head">
               <head>Head 15.</head>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Holineſs and good Works are neceſſary to Salvation.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Conciliatiion.</label> Good Works are ſo, as they are the Proviſion and Preparation of God; even of his Eternal free Grace, in furniſhing us with them; and as we are his <hi>Workmanſhip in Christ Jeſus, Created to them.</hi> But the Number, Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, Elevation of them in higher or lower Degrees of Excellency, ſo diverſe in Saints, ſhew, the Foundation of our Salvation, as well as Juſtification, reſts elſewhere.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="head">
               <head>Head 16.</head>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Good Works are profitable, and pleaſe God.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Conciliation.</label> They do ſo, as they are the Fruits of the Death and Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Jeſus Chriſt, and the Diſpoſalls of his free Grace in us, and to us, and ſo by us; And as God is pleas'd to ſhew himſelf, as the Supreme Rector and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor,
<pb facs="tcp:102302:13"/> according to his Holy Law; but yet ſo, that the Poles on which Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion moves, are the Grace of God in our Election, and his Acceptation of us to Righteouſneſs in Chriſt; and if he leave any of his Servants, in their Service and Good Works to the <hi>Eleventh Hour,</hi> or that he fits them not to ſuch Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant Services, Eminency, and Exemplarineſs therein, as he doth other of his Saints; He hath an Infinite Fund to ſupply them out of, <hi>viz.</hi> the Righteouſneſs, and Obedience of Chriſt; and Power of Grace to Accompliſh them to their Meaſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="head">
               <head>Head 16.</head>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Our Good ſhould be intended by Good Works.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Conciliation.</label> Our Good ſhould be intended by them, as they are Manifeſtations of the Grace of Chriſt in us, and ſuitable to that Law, he influences his Servants by his Spirit according to; In the want of which we have great reaſon to Mourn, as giving Fear and Suſpition Chriſt is <hi>not in us of a Truth;</hi> and that he leaves us to do the things very diſpleaſing, and offenſive to his Holy Nature, and the Rule of Life and Action, his Grace governs his Servants by; but yet they are not of themſelves our Title, but our Evidences only of our Title, which is Chriſt alone; and if we are his, we ſhall certainly be born up to what, He, as our Mediator, Surety, and Teſtator, hath thought neceſſary to our Salvation; and will accept; and ſupply the want of by himſelf; Yet all is, and ought ſo to be carried, that we may be urg'd, and preſs'd to our Duty, as under the Holy Rectory of God, and Chriſt, and according to all the Rules of his Word.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="head">
               <head>Head 17.</head>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Aſſurance is by Goſpel-Marks, and not by a Voice within us.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Conciliation.</label> Marks are according to Scripture; yet ſo, that they are, but few, of any of the Servants of God, but have reaſon to fly to the Witneſs of the Spirit, and its Voice, crying, <hi>Abba, Father;</hi> and to appeal to Infinite Grace; ſeeing in the midſt of our Falls, Failings, and Imperfections, we cannot otherwiſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, where Sincerity and Perfect Obedience divide one from another, and what is enough in our many Corruptions to conſtitute Sincerity. Beſides, ſeeing our Staple-hold is the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt without us, our Supreme Teſtimony depends upon his Spirit, witneſſing within us indeed, yet from what is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out us, <hi>viz.</hi> Free Grace.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="head">
               <head>Head 18.</head>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">God charges Sin on Men, and they ſhould repent for Repeated Pardons.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Conciliation.</label> This is among the Wiſe, Holy, and Gracious Methods of God, and Chriſt, in this preſent Low State of the Redemption, appearing; until its Glory in the <hi>Kingdom of Christ;</hi> that Sin is charg'd, and Pardon repeatedly begg'd in Daily Prayers; But all notwithſtanding is ſecur'd in the unchangeable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Electing Love, of Juſtifying Grace, of the daily Iſſuing Pardon of the <hi>New Covenant,</hi> immediately ready; and thus expreſs'd, as if it iſſued out upon the very Sin; <hi>I will be merciful to their unrighteouſneſſes,</hi> and <hi>their Sins,</hi> and <hi>Iniquities I will remember no more,</hi> Heb. 8. 12. Before <hi>David</hi> had ſaid any more, than this, <hi>I have ſinned against the Lord, Nathan</hi> ſaid from God, <hi>The Lord hath put away the Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of thy Sin, Thou ſhalt not Dye,</hi> 2 Sam. 12. 13. The Grace of the Covenant went forward therefore in him, (as in all Saints) to the Compoſure of his Heart to that great Penitential <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. So that in a way of Conſolation of
<pb facs="tcp:102302:14"/> Saints and Encouraging of all to Come into Chriſt; there may be great Freedom of Expreſſion us'd; in which ſome Things may need Review and Correction, as Humane; and yet the main Scope and Intention preſerv'd, as conſiſtent with ſincere Deſign to promote Holineſs; moſt livelily flowing from the Grace of the Covenant, and the Death of Chriſt, into the Hearts and Lives of Believers; there being hence much more hope, both in Converſion and Renewed Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, than in any thing within Men themſelves; whenever they have fallen into Sin after converſion, or while in an unconverted eſtate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="head">
               <head>Head.</head>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Sin may hurt Believers, and God afflicts for Sin.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Conciliation.</label> While we look down to the preſent State, and to God's preſent Government of the World, this muſt be acknowledg'd; and yet when we lift up our Hearts to the Conſideration of the Supreme Grace of God in Jeſus Chriſt, the very hurt Sin does Believers, or even the Elect, is made to ſerve the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs of Grace; and all their Afflictions for Sin are Salutary Diſpenſations. All which muſt needs be granted on cloſe reaſoning theſe Points, and will bear out many Amplifications of this Grace in Diſcourſes declararatory of it; tho' on the other ſide, a very different way of ſpeaking of them muſt be ſubmitted to in this <hi>Atmoſphere,</hi> this Dark and Foul Place of the <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> we are yet in; and it is born out by a very general way of Scripture-ſpeaking.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="head">
               <head>Head 19.</head>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Sincere Holineſs is not <hi>Dung;</hi> nor does the Apoſtle include ſuch Holineſs in that ſo great Scripture concerning <hi>Evangelical Righteouſneſs,</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip. 3. 7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Conciliation.</label> For the clearing of that great Scripture, and the Points depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent upon it, I muſt firſt take the freedom to aſſert; That the Apoſtle doth in that Context, lay down at full and at large, the two great Points of <hi>Juſtification</hi> and <hi>Sanctification:</hi> In that of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> he riſes to the heighth, and ſo in that of <hi>Sanctification;</hi> and theſe are both handled ſo diſtinctly, that they cannot be confounded.</p>
               <p>For the Apoſtle had fallen ſeverely upon the <hi>Conciſion;</hi> by whom he moſt probably means, thoſe who compounded the Profeſſion of Chriſtianity with the <hi>Works</hi> and <hi>Ritualiſms of the Law;</hi> as if Chriſt were not enough without them, for <hi>Acceptance with God,</hi> for <hi>Righteouſneſs in Juſtification,</hi> and <hi>Holineſs in Sanctification;</hi> and therefore he calls them not, <hi>The Circumciſion,</hi> meaning Pure and Perfect Jews; but the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>the Conciſion,</hi> as a Peculiar Brand of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach upon Them; and calls Himſelf, and Sincere Chriſtians, The Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Spiritual Circumciſion,</hi> who <hi>Worſhip God in Spirit;</hi> who hold the True <hi>Righteouſneſs of Faith;</hi> of which it was the <hi>Seal; Rejoyce in Christ Jeſus</hi> alone, and have <hi>no confidence in the Fleſh;</hi> that is, in Creature Righteouſneſs; In the ſame ſenſe <hi>Fleſh</hi> is taken, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 1. <hi>What ſhall we ſay, that Abraham our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath found, according to the Fleſh, viz.</hi> according to his own Righteouſneſs, not only Ceremonial, but Moral; For if <hi>Abraham</hi> were <hi>juſtified</hi> by <hi>Works,</hi> &amp;c. So: But if he had no other way, but to believe on him that <hi>juſtifieth</hi> the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly.</hi> It is evident, it was not Ceremonial Ritual Works, the Apoſtle diſcourſed of, but Subſtantial Works of Righteouſneſs, oppoſed to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſs.</hi> Thus the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle reckoning up his own Priviledges firſt, gives indeed thoſe, which were
<pb facs="tcp:102302:14"/> External, and Ritual, but adds Moral in thoſe words; According to the <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> which was not only Ceremonial but Moral, <hi>He was Blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs;</hi> which words may be expounded by thoſe; <hi>I have liv'd in all good Conſcience before God to this day,</hi> Acts 23. 1.</p>
               <p>Now, upon all this, he ſits as an Accountant, with his Tables before him, and what had been <hi>Gain or Riches</hi> in his Account, he now writes it, All Cypher; And then, by way of Triumph, and in a mighty Elevation of his Diſcourſe, he adds, <hi>Yea, doubtleſs, I count not only my Jewiſh</hi> (as I may call them) <hi>Effects;</hi> but even whatever elſe may come into Computation; even All he accounted <hi>Loſs,</hi> of no Value: On what Recompence or Reparation did the Apoſtle thus caſt out every thing? On this alone, <hi>That he might be found in Christ, not having his own Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> which is <hi>of the Law;</hi> but that which is the <hi>Righteouſneſs of Christ,</hi> the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> which <hi>is by Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To clear the Apoſtle's Doctrine; Theſe two great Doubts muſt be decided,</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Query I.</label>Whether the Apoſtle thus far, as we have gone, is upon the Point of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> or of <hi>Sanctification;</hi> or ſo much as on <hi>Sanctification</hi> join'd with <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification;</hi> or on <hi>Juſtification</hi> purely, and alone, when he ſpeaks thus?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Quer. II.</label>Whether the Apoſtle puts into this Account of <hi>Loſs</hi> and <hi>Dung,</hi> the Inherent Holineſs, he had as a Chriſtian; looking upon it, as Inherent, and in Himſelf; whether, I ſay, he accounted this, as <hi>Loſs</hi> and <hi>Dung,</hi> or only the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial, Ritual, Righteouſneſs of the <hi>Law,</hi> together with his Pretentions to the Moral Righteouſneſs of it, as without Chriſt, and ſeparated from him?</p>
               <p>The clear Deciſion of theſe two Queſtions, will much contribute to our diſtinct Judgment in the Points we are upon.</p>
               <div n="1" type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer to Query I.</head>
                  <p>I aſſert therefore, thus far as I have gone upon this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text, or till the Apoſtle comes to thoſe words; That I may <hi>know Him,</hi> and the <hi>Power of his Reſurrection;</hi> he is wholly and ſolely upon the Point of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> and not of <hi>Sanctification.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Argument 1.</label>The Apoſtles does in all his Solemn Diſcourſes moſt diſtinctly handle the Point and Doctrine of <hi>Juſtification</hi> by it ſelf, and of <hi>Sanctification</hi> by it ſelf; ſo <hi>Rom.</hi> c. 3. c. 4. c. 5. he begins with <hi>Juſtification,</hi> and ſo goes on to <hi>Sanctification, c.</hi> 6. ſo <hi>Gal.</hi> c. 3. he diſcourſes of <hi>Juſtification;</hi> and the conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of it, <hi>c.</hi> 4. and ſo enters into that of <hi>Sanctification, c.</hi> 5. c. 6. Even in all the Apoſtolick Epiſtles, we may find, the Lines of <hi>Juſtification</hi> and <hi>Sanctification</hi> are kept diſtinct, and clear, one from the other. So therefore here it is to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected he ſhould do; for the Goſpel-Notions are moſt diſtinct.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Arg. 2.</label>The <hi>Righteouſneſs of God</hi> without the <hi>Law,</hi> Rom. 3. 21, 22, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is the <hi>Righteouſneſs of Juſtification.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Arg. 3.</label>
                     <hi>Righteouſneſs by Faith,</hi> is a peculiar manner of Speaking in the Point of <hi>Juſtification; Juſtified by Faith,</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs of Faith,</hi> is ſeveral times men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd in the Diſcourſe of Juſtification, <hi>Rom.</hi> c. 3. c. 4. in thoſe great and moſt diſtinct Treaties of Juſtification, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Arg. 4.</label>The Expreſſion of being <hi>Found in Christ,</hi> being ſo plain an Alluſion to the <hi>Cities of Refuge,</hi> the Security from the <hi>Avengers of Blood;</hi> plainly ſhews, The Apoſtle was upon the Point of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> our great Security againſt
<pb facs="tcp:102302:15"/> Guilt, Wrath, and Condemnation, at the Times when the Purſuits will be clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt upon us.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Arg. 5.</label>The Firſt, and Fundamental Riches of every Man is that Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, by which we ſtand before God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Arg. 6.</label>That which is oppos'd to the <hi>Righteouſneſs of the Law,</hi> which was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Covenant of Works</hi> to juſtifie, is the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt for <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification;</hi> ſo no other can be meant.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Arg. 7.</label>The Apoſtle goes on to ſo ſolemn a Diſcourſe of <hi>Sanctification;</hi> in the moſt proper Expreſſions of it, Source and Springs of it, and to the utmoſt Heighths of it; and ſo conſequent and dependent upon his being <hi>Found in Christ</hi> for <hi>Juſtification;</hi> that it is an Injury to his Diſcourſe to Confound the Foregoing ſo proper to <hi>Juſtification,</hi> with thoſe ſo proper to <hi>Sanctification,</hi> as ſhall be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently made further out.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="answer">
                  <head>Anſ. to Quer. II.</head>
                  <p>I aſſert, in anſwer to <hi>Query</hi> II. There is great reaſon to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, the Apoſtle put into the Account, or Bill of his Effects, the <hi>Holineſs,</hi> he had as a Chriſtian, conſidered as inherent in himſelf, but not as in Chriſt; ſo that even this he accounted but as Loſs, and of vile Account in the Point of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Argument 1.</label>Becauſe by way of Elevation and Surmount, above all he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>before ſaid, of Ritual or Moral Legal Righteouſneſs; the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>Yea, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, I count all Things;</hi> Now what All, or Any could there be in Relation to God, between God and the Soul, beyond what he had Named, but what he had, as a Chriſtian; as in Himſelf, but not as in Chriſt. And hereunto agrees that vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Perſon, Dr. <hi>Tuckney,</hi> in his Sermons on <hi>Philip.</hi> 3. p. 42.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Arg. 2.</label>That Expreſſion of being <hi>Found in Christ, viz.</hi> Chriſt himſelf; ſhews; a Chriſtian cannot reſt, in what he hath, though from Chriſt; in himſelf, as a Chriſtian; except he be found in Chriſt himſelf.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Arg. 3.</label>Becauſe all the Holineſs of a Chriſtian, as it is in himſelf, and not in Chriſt, comes under the denomination of his <hi>own Righteouſneſs,</hi> and even of the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of the <hi>Law;</hi> For it can be no other than the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of that <hi>Law,</hi> which is <hi>Spiritual, Holy, Just,</hi> and <hi>Good;</hi> And to aſſert any other Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of Sanctification, as to the Matter, is a greater <hi>Antinomianiſm,</hi> or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>levation of the Law of God, than any other thing call'd ſo loudly <hi>Antinomia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Arg. 4.</label>The Holineſs, Majeſty, Purity of God, is infinitely great; we cannot ſtand before him, but in the increated Righteouſneſs of Chriſt alone. Angelical Righteouſneſs is call'd <hi>Folly,</hi> and is <hi>unclean before Him;</hi> What wonder is it then, our Holineſs, however receiv'd from Chriſt, is, as in us, in the midſt of remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sin, call'd <hi>Dung,</hi> even as Filthy Rags, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64. 6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="objection_and_answer">
                  <head>Object.</head>
                  <p>But can the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Sanctification</hi> from Chriſt, be ſtiled <hi>Droſs,</hi> or <hi>Dung,</hi> of which the Apoſtle, juſt after, deſir'd ſo high Attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw.</label> We ought to diſtinguiſh between the Holineſs of <hi>Sanctification,</hi> as it is in a perpetual Emanation from Chriſt, from his <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> from his <hi>Death,</hi> from his <hi>Reſurrection;</hi> and as it is in us mixed, and allayed with the remaining
<pb facs="tcp:102302:15"/> Corruption in the beſt of Saints: in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> be called <hi>Loſs</hi> or <hi>Dung;</hi> for it is conſider'd in Chriſt the Fountain, and ſo as from him to us, where it is pure and unmix'd; under his <hi>Sacrifice; the Blood of the Everlaſting Covenant,</hi> the Power of the <hi>endleſs Life</hi> ſtreaming out always upon it: But as in us, if conſidered as ſeparate from Chriſt; It is as a Beam clip'd off from the Sun, that would preſently vaniſh, and come to nothing, or ſink into our Darkneſs and Impurity: It is the great Admonition therefore of the Apoſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 1. <hi>My Son, be ſtrong in the Grace that is in Jeſus Christ.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And to ſhew how earneſtly Chriſtians ſhould preſs to the height of theſe Emana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from the <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Reſurrection of Chriſt;</hi> he lays down that great <hi>Canon</hi> never Calculated for any Poor, Baſe, Ritual Conformity; never in the Apoſtles Thoughts; But it is fitted to that great end, <hi>viz. To Attain, if it were poſſible, the Holineſs of the Reſurrection of the Dead;</hi> And for this to <hi>forget All,</hi> that is <hi>behind;</hi> And to <hi>preſs according to the Mark, for the Prize,</hi> but not by the way of any thing we can do, but from God above, alone, <hi>viz.</hi> by the <hi>High Calling of God in Christ,</hi> and not by our own Strength, but as <hi>apprehended of Chriſt</hi> for it; By this <hi>Canon</hi> all the <hi>Perfect, Perfect</hi> in regard of <hi>Sincerity, Walk, though</hi> they <hi>count</hi> not themſelves <hi>Perfect</hi> otherwiſe; This Apoſtle, and therefore no Apoſtle did ſo <hi>Count;</hi> For he was <hi>not behind the chiefest:</hi> They all then walk'd by this <hi>Canon;</hi> If any <hi>Perfect</hi> or Sincere be never ſo little <hi>otherwiſe minded,</hi> God <hi>reveals</hi> even this great Purſuit, and End to them; That ſo far as they have <hi>attained,</hi> whatever it be, they ſhould <hi>Forget what is behind,</hi> and <hi>preſs Forward,</hi> Mind that Point, the Holineſs of <hi>the Reſurrection:</hi> To raiſe the Spirits of his Saints to which, though they had not attain'd to it, at the going out of the Body; yet in a <hi>Moment,</hi> in the <hi>Twinckling</hi> of an Eye, in an Indiviſible Point of Time, Chriſt <hi>apprehends them;</hi> Even then, and with a greater Eaſe, in the Nature of the Thing, then he raiſes their <hi>Bodies Incorru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptible;</hi> having hold of them for that very thing; even by the mighty <hi>Power of his own Death</hi> and <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> whereby he is able to <hi>Subdue all Things unto himſelf.</hi> This <hi>Canon</hi> had never been ſo depretiated as to be applyed to any Outward Form, or Church-Order, as it is call'd, if the greatneſs of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Point had been conſidered; and for which, there is not any Ombrage here; except that the Word, <hi>Canon,</hi> which has been ſo <hi>Debauched</hi> by the working of the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity,</hi> puts any one in Mind of it; For only according to the preſent occaſion, its taken by the Apoſtle from the <hi>Olympick</hi> Races to the great purpoſe of the New <hi>Creation, Gal.</hi> 6. 16. and here to ſhew the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an's Rule or Line, is up to the higheſt Holineſs, even that of the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Thus large have I been on this Head, becauſe it is of ſo great Moment.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="head">
               <head>Head 20.</head>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Chriſt does not Repent and Believe for us.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Conciliation.</label> Chriſt, hath yet laid the Foundation of all our State in Grace and Glory in himſelf, and in his own Action; wherein we are to be made like him, as from the Archetype and Life; <hi>He took part of Fleſh and Blood,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Children were Partakers;</hi> He was <hi>Circumciſed, Baptized, Dyed, Roſe</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:102302:16"/> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Juſtifieth me, who will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with me?</hi> That <hi>Agony,</hi> wherein He ſweat <hi>Drops of Blood,</hi> ſtanding under the Senſe of the Sins of All, for whom he Dyed, and made <hi>Supplication with ſtrong Crys and Tears</hi> unto him, that was able <hi>to ſave him from Death, and was Heard, in that he Fear'd;</hi> was, as it were, the great <hi>Penitential</hi> of the <hi>Redeemer</hi> in the Behalf, and as in the Perſon of his <hi>Redeemed;</hi> And as for Faith; It is written, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 13. <hi>I will put my Truſt in him.</hi> Thus all our Springs are in him, and from him; and the Efficacies, that <hi>Work all our Works in us, and for us.</hi> They are ſo veſted in our Faculties and Action, that they are in us; and yet by ſo Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme a Vertue from him, reſiding in him, and given us as in a Line of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication from him to us, That they are <hi>wrought</hi> by him <hi>for us;</hi> And in this rightly underſtood Senſe, he may be ſaid to <hi>Repent</hi> and <hi>Believe</hi> for us, though alſo in us, and by us.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <p>The three laſt Heads, concerning Goſpel Preaching, have been all along aimed to be thus determin'd; That it is certain; Both Conditional Preaching, and Abſolute Preaching, have each their reſpective Foundations in Scripture; And both tend to the ſame end, to ſhew the Abſolute Neceſſity of Chriſt, and Grace from him; As alſo the Abſolute Neceſſity of Holineſs; as indeed, the Thing is; flowing from the <hi>Grace</hi> of <hi>Election,</hi> through the Efficacies of the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator by his Spirit; as the greateſt Scriptures concerning our Salvation, witneſs; Yet for Wiſe and Holy Purpoſes ſo Adminiſtred, that our Action is all manner of ways inſiſted upon by the general Courſe of Scripture, as hath been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd: So that none are to be blamed in the Abundance of their Miniſtry in that part, who do more continually in their Preaching, and ſometimes in moſt ſolemn Diſcourſes, ſet out Chriſt, <hi>The only VVay, the Truth and the Life,</hi> flowing from the Eternal Fountain of <hi>Electing Love</hi> and <hi>Grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if we compare one part of Preaching with another, ſeeing the Life of all Conditional Preaching depends on the Abſolute <hi>Grace of the Covenant;</hi> That muſt needs be the moſt excellent part of Preaching, wherein the Life of the other is laid up, and to which the other is but ſubordinated; But as we find, Scripture gives Example of the Conditional Preaching, as the more general; So it ſeems moſt adapted and ſuited to this low State of the Adminiſtration of the Redemption of Chriſt; and we find, the Divine Spirit, who <hi>Divides to All his Servants, as he will,</hi> does more generally and univerſally move the Preachers of the Goſpel, more abundantly into this Conditional Preaching.</p>
               <p>But when that better State, that higher Adminiſtration of the Redemption of Chriſt in his Kingdom ſhall come on, as it is now very near; That, <hi>as it were a new Song,</hi> which hath been ſo much out of uſe; it is, as it were, <hi>a new Song;</hi> at leaſt in its high Mount <hi>Zion</hi> Senſes; even, I ſay, notwithſtanding ſo much of it recovered into uſe by <hi>the Reformation.</hi> This Song, of the Redemption of Chriſt, in more lofty Ayrs ſhall be Heard, and Learnt; as hath been already ſaid; by all the Illuſtrious Aſſiſtants, or By-Standers, and <hi>Followers of the Lamb on Mount</hi> Zion.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:102302:16"/>
               <p> In the mean time God does raiſe up ſome, who aſpire to theſe Truths of the higheſt Excellency, and, as we ſay, of the firſt Magnitude, and higheſt Eleva<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion; and ſuch was Dr. <hi>Criſp,</hi> in my Account; But becauſe we are yet in this dark and low State, there are many Infirmities, much Rudeneſs of Speech, want of <hi>Mightineſs in Word</hi> and <hi>Deed</hi> in ſuch Aſpirings; an Univerſal want of the Glory and Holineſs flowing from theſe great <hi>Truths,</hi> becauſe theſe Truths are not come into their proper Time of Glory: This <hi>Song</hi> cannot be <hi>Sung,</hi> while the <hi>Babel</hi> State yet continues, becauſe it was the Lord's <hi>Song,</hi> and cannot be Sung, in a ſtrange Land, to Perfection; by reaſon of which theſe great Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines are under a Veil, and not only ſo, but under great Prejudice. Let us therefore earneſtly prary, theſe Miſts, theſe Shades and Clouds, may fly away; and yet even the unwarineſſes of Expreſſion in ſuch, as Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi> are over-ruled by God, like the <hi>ſpeaking of Stones,</hi> to make the main Preaching more <hi>notable,</hi> and to excite our Reſearch of them.</p>
               <p>Theſe things are written for Reconciliation, not Exaſperation; and that we may be all ſtir'd up earneſtly to pray, <hi>That the Day may break, and the Shadows fly away, and our Beloved come on his Mount of Spices.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="list_of_heads">
            <head>
               <hi>SOME General HEADS. OF Mr.</hi> Williams<hi>'s, Conciliated in this Diſcourſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>THE Elect are Children of Wrath, till effectually called.</item>
               <item>The Filth of Sin not tranſacted on Chriſt.</item>
               <item>The Act of laying Sins on Chriſt, is not the Diſcharge of the Elect.</item>
               <item>Mens Sins their own, and not Christ's Sins.</item>
               <item>Our Sins laid on Chriſt, before he was nailed to the Croſs.</item>
               <item>Chriſt not abhorred by the Father.</item>
               <item>No change of Perſon between Chriſt and the Elect.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:102302:17"/>
               <item>Chriſt's Mediatorial Righteouſneſs not ſubjectively in us, and how im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted.</item>
               <item>Believers not as Holy as Chriſt.</item>
               <item>The Covenant of Grace explained, and what a Condition is.</item>
               <item>The Covenant of Grace Conditional.</item>
               <item>Faith not a Perſwaſion that my Sins are pardoned, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Prevailing Enmity, a Hindrance to our preſent Intereſt in Chriſt.</item>
               <item>The Elect not united to Chriſt without Faith.</item>
               <item>What <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion with Chriſt is.</item>
               <item>Juſtification not before Faith.</item>
               <item>Repentance neceſſary to Pardon.</item>
               <item>Sinners have much to do to be Saved.</item>
               <item>The Goſpel hath Threats and Promiſes.</item>
               <item>Happineſs and Good Works neceſſary to Salvation.</item>
               <item>They are profitable, and God pleaſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Our own Good ſhould be intended.</item>
               <item>Aſſurance by Goſpel-Marks, and not by an Inward Voice</item>
               <item>God Chargeth Sin on Men, and they ſhould repent for repeated Pardon.</item>
               <item>Sin may hurt Believers.</item>
               <item>God afflicts for Sin.</item>
               <item>Sincere Holineſs not Dung.</item>
               <item>Chriſt doth not repent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for us.</item>
               <item>Conditional Propoſals of Benefits on Terms of Duty, Goſpel-Preaching.</item>
               <item>To excite Fear in ſenſe of Danger, not Legal Preaching.</item>
               <item>Chriſt more Exalted by the former Truths, than Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi>'s Opinions.</item>
               <item>The Free Grace of God not honoured by Dr. <hi>Criſp,</hi> though more Freeneſs be aſſerted by him, than by theſe Truths.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>The END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:102302:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
